My name is Talal Mustafa al-Shuweimi
"اسمي "طلال مصطفى الشويمي
I’m from Raqqa Province, living on Sajiyah Street
من محافظة الرقة، من سكان شارع الساجية
I’m 45 years old
عمري 45 عاماً
I have 3 wives and 13 children
لديّ 3 زوجات و 13 طفلاً
During the Assad regime’s control of Raqqa, I worked at the Water Department
مهنتي أثناء سيطرة النظام السوري على مدينة الرقة، كنت موظفاً في مؤسسة المياه
After the problems and battles started
وبعد المشاكل والمعارك
I was dismissed from work
فصلت من العمل لأسباب
The regime accused me of being a terrorist
لدى النظام السوري على أني إرهابي
The Air Force Intelligence raided my house
وتمت مداهمتي من قبل المخابرات الجوية
Because they claimed I was a terrorist
على أني إرهابي
The dismissal order came from Damascus
وجاء قرار فصلي من دمشق
Of course
طبعاً
It was all a malicious report
هذا الشيء كله تقرير كيدي
Because we were locals and stayed in the city
لأننا نحن أولاد البلد وبقينا في البلد
My dismissal order came in 2012
حيث جاء قرار فصلي في عام 2012
So I fled Raqqa for a while
فهربت من محافظة الرقة لفترة زمنية
And my brother was arrested
وأخي اعتقله
By the Assad regime
النظام السوري
On behalf of the regime
لصالح النظام
They put him in Sednaya Prison for about 6 years
ووضعوه في سجن صيدنايا، لمدة 6 سنوات تقريباً
After they detained my brother for 6 years in prison
بعدما اعتقلوا أخي ووضعوه لمدة 6 سنوات في السجن
The Free Syrian Army entered Raqqa
جاءنا الجيش الحر ودخل مدينة الرقة
I was already dismissed from work as a “terrorist”
طبعاً تم فصلي من الوظيفة باسم إرهابي
About 6 or 7 months after the FSA entered
وبعد دخول الجيش الحر بما يقارب 6 أو 7 أشهر
ISIS entered the city, calling itself the Islamic State
دخلت علينا دولة داعش باسم الدولة الإسلامية
They took control of the area
ودخلوا إلى البلد
Within their first 2 or 3 months of settling in
وفي أول دخولهم واستقرارهم ما بين 2 أو 3 أشهر
They arrested me, accusing me of being a regime agent,a shabiha [pro-regime thug]
"اعتقلوني بتهمة عميل للنظام السوري "شبّيح
They detained me at Point 11, with the security members
اعتقلوني في النقطة 11 عند الأمنيين
Inside the former Governor’s Palace
داخل قصر المحافظ سابقاً
I stayed there for about a week
وبقيت هناك مدة أسبوع تقريباً
After the Governor’s Palace, they took me
وبعد قصر المحافظ، أخذوني
To a new security base near the National Hospital area in Raqqa
حيث أسسوا نقطة أمنية جديدة في منطقة نزلة المشفى الوطني في مدينة الرقة
It was inside the old Military Judiciary building of the Assad regime
وتقع في بناء القضاء العسكري التابع سابقاً للنظام السوري
A week later, they moved me from the Governor’s Palace basement
نقلوني بعد أسبوع من مبنى المحافظة وأخذوني من القبو الأرضي
To the old Military Judiciary building near the Traffic Circle
إلى مبنى القضاء العسكري قديماً والذي يقع عند منطقة نزلة المرور
I stayed in that base
وبقيت في هذه النقطة
Under the same charge, regime agent
وكانت التهمة عميل للنظام السوري
I stayed there for 53 days
وبقيت في هذه النقطة 53 يوماً
After 53 days
وبعد 53 يوماً
They released me because there was no evidence against me
أخلوا سبيلي لأنه لا يوجد عليّ أدلة مثبتة
The one who interrogated me
الذي حقق معي
Was from Raqqa Province, from Tabqa city
شخص من محافظة الرقة من مدينة الطبقة
His family name was Khameesi
"وأصله "خميسي
He was called Abu Yousuf, the interrogator
"يدعى "أبو يوسف تحقيق
He was the head of interrogators
وهو رئيس المحققين
Another man was nicknamed Abu Abdurrahman
"ويوجد شخص آخر ملقب "أبو عبد الرحمن
His name was Mahmoud al-Ali al-Sahou from the Ghanem al-Zahir clan
"اسمه "محمود العلي السهو "من "عشيرة الغانم الظاهر
From an area called al-Jaif
"من منطقة تسمى "الجايف
East of the al-Eywij area
"حول شرقي منطقة "الإعيوج
Near Rashid Farm in Raqqa
بالقرب من "مزرعة الرشيد" في مدينة الرقة
I stayed under interrogation for about 53 days
بقيّت في التحقيق ما يقارب 53 يوماً
After they confirmed there was nothing against me
بعدما أثبتوا أنه لا يوجد عليّ شيء
They realized I’d already been dismissed by the Assad regime as a “terrorist”
وتبيّن لهم أنني فصلت سابقاً من قبل النظام السوري بتهمة الإرهاب
So they released me
فأخلوا سبيلي
And gave me a clearance card
وأعطوني بطاقة براءة
A certificate proving there were no charges against me
شهادة براءة تثبت عدم وجود شيء عليّ
As a Syrian citizen
فكوني مواطن سوري
And a Sunni by faith
وسني العقيدة
I went back to work with the other workers
عدت للدوام إلى وظيفتي مع باقي العمال
Trying to earn a living to support my children
أترزق الله ولكي أصرف على أطفالي
Around 50 or 60 days after returning
فتفاجأت بعد رجوعي بما يقارب 50 أو 60 يوماً
I was surprised to see someone
وجدت شخصاً
Sadly, he was from the same neighborhood, Sunni, and a local of the area
وللأسف الشديد أنه من أولاد البلد وسني العقيدة ومن أبناء الحي ذاته أيضاً
His name was Mahmoud al-Shahada
"اسمه "محمود الشحادة
He was an ISIS emir overseeing the Water Department
وهو أمير لدى التنظيم يترأس مؤسسة المياه
Known as Abu Hudhayfa
"الملقب "أبو حذيفة
Abu Hudhayfa had been detained in Assad regime prisons back in 2000
طبعاً "أبو حذيفة" في عام 2000 كان معتقل سابق في سجون نظام الأسد
Accused of joining Jund al-Sham
بتهمة انتسابه لجند الشام
He struck a deal with the regime in Sednaya Prison and was released
وعقد صفقة مع النظام السوري في سجن "صيدنايا" وأخلوا سبيله
Then brought to Raqqa and appointed as an emir in the caliphate
وأحضروه إلى مدينة الرقة وأدخلوه كأمير في الخلافة هنا
Mahmoud al-Shahada, known as Abu Hudhayfa, and his brother were both active and skilled
"و"محمود الشحادة" الملقب "أبو حذيفة كونه لديه اجتهادات وعمل جيد هو وأخوه
His brother’s name was Hassan
"واسم أخيه "حسان
He had two brothers, Hassan and Hassaan
"ولديه اثنان من الأخوة هما "حسان وحسن
His brother was an emir and his right-hand man
أخوه كان أميراً ويده اليمين
When I came back to the Water Department
وعندما أتيت أنا إلى مؤسسة المياه
I was surprised he’d become the department’s emir after being released from Sednaya
فتفاجأت أنه أصبح أمير المؤسسة "وقد خرج من سجن "صيدنايا
When the workers learned I was coming to work again
عندما علموا العمال أني بدأت في الذهاب معهم إلى الدوام
I had no salary, but people gave us charity for the children
وطبعاً لم يكن لدي راتب شهري ولكن الناس كانت تتزكى علينا من أجل الأطفال
They offered us odd jobs outside
ويعطوننا عمل خارجي
Of course, we had no fixed income since I and others were dismissed from work
وبالطبع لم يكن لدينا راتب ثابت لكوننا مفصولين من العمل أنا وكم شخص آخر
Then Abu Hudhayfa came
"جاء "أبو حذيفة
And arrested me himself,Mahmoud al-Shahada
"واعتقلني، هو الذي اسمه "محمود الشحادة
By then, he’d become “Minister of the Caliphate” because of his influence and knowledge
وكان استلم منصب وزير الخلافة كونه أصبح لديه اجتهادات ومعارف في البلد
He had many initiatives, so he arrested me
كانت اجتهاداته كثيرة، فاعتقلني
He tricked me into it
(طبعاً اعتقلني بالحيلة (احتال عليّ
At the time, we were fixing a broken water line
في تلك الأيام كنا نعمل على إصلاح خط مياه مكسور
In the Khasra Faraj area, and when we came
في منطقة "الكسرة فرج" وعندما أتينا
He said, “The sheikh wants to see you”
قال لي: طلبك الشيخ فلان
“He wants to ask a few questions, and there’s also a broken pipe at the security point”
ويريد أن يسألك عدة أسئلة كما هناك خط مياه مكسور في النقطة الأمنية ذاتها
He said, “You should fix it.” I said, “As you wish, Abu Hudhayfa”
مكسور يجب أن تصلحوه "قلت له: كرمت عيناك يا "أبو حذيفة
When I arrived there, I only saw weapons pointed at me
وبعدما ذهبت إلى هناك لم أرَ سوى السلاح لقُّم عليّ
They threw me to the ground, stepped on my neck, and arrested me
وألقوني أرضاً ودعسوا على رقبتي واعتقلوني
For about two months
لمدة شهرين تقريباً
When I returned to work at the Water Department
وعندما عدت للعمل في مؤسسة المياه
Abu Hudhayfa grabbed me by the hair
أمسكني "أبو حذيفة" من شعر رأسي
Dragged me toward the table
وسحبني إلى الطاولة
Pressed my head onto it
ووضع رأسي على الطاولة
And placed his foot on my left shoulder
ووضع قدمه على كتفي الأيسر
He said to me, “You’re a shabih (pro-regime thug). You shouldn’t enter the institution. You’re an agent for the regime”
وقال لي: "أنت شخص شبيح "لا يجب أن تدخل المؤسسة، أنت عميل للنظام
I told him, Calm down, Sheikh, this is my clearance from Point 11, and I’m clean, there’s nothing against me
قلت له: اهدأ يا شيخ هذه براءتي من النقطة 11 وأنا شخص لا يوجد عليّ شيء
I have children, but he said, No, you’re a shabih
ويوجد لدي أطفال، فقال لي: لا أنت شبيح
And no one will be able to get you back to work
ولن يستطيع أحد أن يعيدك إلى العمل
We brought mediations from one sheikh and another, but nothing worked
أحضرنا وساطات من شيخ فلان وشيخ فلان ولم ينفع الأمر
At that point, I had a small amount of money
وهنا كان لدي مبلغ صغير
And my brother had about 125,000 Syrian pounds
وعند أخي مبلغ ما يقارب 125 ألف سوري
So I bought a taxi
فاشتريت سيارة أجرة
A taxi with no official papers
تكسي ليس لها أوراق رسمية
Back then they used to call it “Arouriya”
"وكان يطلق عليها في تلك الفترة اسم "عرعورية
Because it was stolen,they’d steal and sell it without papers
كونها مسروقة يسرقونها ويبيعونها من دون أوراق
So they called it an “Arouriya car”
"فيطقلون عليها اسم "سيارة عرورية
I worked as a taxi driver
عملت سائق سيارة أجرة
For about 5 to 6 months
تقريباً لمدة 5 إلى 6 أشهر
One day
جاء يوم من الأيام
The Hisba (religious police) raided me at my home
فداهمتني الحسبة، حيث كنت أسكن
On 16th Street
بشارع 16
They said to me, You’re a man who trades cigarettes
قالوا لي: أنت رجل تتاجر بالسجائر
And they detained me for 4 days
واعتقلوني لمدة 4 أيام
They insulted me, but it wasn’t severe or extreme
طبعاً أهانوني ولكن لم تكن إهانة كبيرة و شديدة
They kept saying, You’re a cigarette dealer, and so on
يقولون لي: أنت تاجر سجائر وما إلى ذلك
I told him, Sheikh, I’m not a cigarette dealer, I don’t even smoke cigarettes, but yes, I smoke hookah
قلت له: يا شيخ أنا لست تاجر سجائر ولا حتى أشرب السجائر ولكن نعم أشرب الأرجيلة
Yes, I smoke hookah
نعم أشرب الأرجيلة
But I don’t smoke cigarettes. If I did, I’d tell you
لكني لا أشرب السجائر لو كنت أشرب السجائر لأخبرتك بذلك
Anyway, they detained me
المهم في ذلك اعتقلوني
One man
شخص
And took me to a Hisba base called “Panorama”
وأخذوني إلى مقر تابع "للحسبة اسمه "البانوراما
It’s in Raqqa, near Maqs Roundabout, called “Panorama”
تقع في منطقة داخل الرقة "بجانب دوار المقص اسمها "البانوراما
There was a Hisba base there. The emir in charge was Abu Bishr
حيث يوجد هناك مقر للحسبة "اسم الأمير المسؤول عنه "أبو بشر
Abu Bishr, a Saudi national
أبو بشر" سعودي الجنسية"
After 4 days of detention
وبعد اعتقالي ب 4 أيام
I moved my home to another neighborhood, fearing someone was targeting me
غيرت عنوان منزلي إلى حي آخر خوفاً من أن يكون أحد ما يتقصد إيذائي
I was hungry, and I had 12 or 13 children
المهم بالأمر، أصابني الجوع ولدي أطفال عددهم 12 و13 طفلاً
There was no strength left in me
ولا حول ولا قوة
I thought, There are people who trade cigarettes and make a living from it
قلت بنفسي، هناك أناس يعملون في تجارة وبيع السجائر وتسترزق منه
So I started selling cigarettes. Honestly, the accusation already stuck to me anyway
فبدأت العمل بتجارة السجائر، والصراحة أن هذه التهمة منسوبة إلي ومنسوبة (أي تحصيل حاصل)
So I decided to trade cigarettes
فقررت العمل بتجارة السجائر
And I began working in that trade
وبدأت العمل بتجارته
For about a month or a month and a half
لمدة شهر أو شهر ونصف تقريباً
Then a Hisba patrol came and arrested me
جاءت دورية الحسبة واعتقلوني
They detained me for about 15 days
فاعتقلوني ما يقارب 15 يوماً
And the one who arrested me
وأول من اعتقلني
Was a man from Rumaila named Mustafa al-Hamid al-Muslih
شخص من منطقة رميلة "اسمه "مصطفى الحامد المصلح
Known as Abu Seif Maqs
"الملقب "أبو سيف مقص
He also had another nom de guerre, Abu Seif Doshka
"وله لقبان "أبو سيف دوشكا
Also known as Abu Seif Maqs
"وملقب أيضاً "أبو سيف مقص
He was originally from the Wahb clan
" أصله من عشيرة "الوهب
His maternal uncles were from the Masaar group of the Barij clan
أخواله جماعة يطلقون عليهم "المسعر" من عشيرة "البريج"
As for Abu Seif Maqs, his past
طبعاً "أبو سيف مقص" بالنسبة لماضيه
Was extremely bad
ماضيه سيء لدرجة كبيرة
He used to take hashish and pills and was unemployed
من تعاطي للحشيش والحبوب والعطالة عن العمل
And strangely enough
وبشكل غريب
When ISIS entered, I was shocked to see he had become a Doshka gunner
وعندما دخلت الدولة الإسلامية تفاجأت أنه أصبح رامي رشاش دوشكا
Then, since he was from the area and knew people
وبعد الدوشكا كونه ابن المنطقة ولديه معارف
They made him emir of the Search and Investigation Unit, this man called Mustafa
فوضعوه أمير في قسم التحري "هذا الشخص الذي يدعى "مصطفى
Mustafa arrested me
"اعتقلني "مصطفى
For the second time, for about 15 days. He tortured, beat, and insulted me
للمرة الثانية لمدة 15 يوماً تقريباً عذبني وضربني وأهانني
Of course, they found no cigarettes with me
طبعاً لم يضبط عندي سجائر
The emir of the Search Unit was the same Mustafa al-Muslih
والذي كان أميراً على التحري "هو نفسه "مصطفى المصلح
Known as Abu Seif
"الملقب "أبو سيف
And another man called Ibrahim al-Ali al-Khayheet
"وشخص آخر يدعى "إبراهيم العلي الكحيط
From the Ghanem al-Zahir clan, living near the Jazra Junction in Raqqa
من عشيرة "الغانم الظاهر" من سكان "مفرق الجزرة" في مدينة الرقة
Known as Abu Hudhayfa
"الملقب "أبو حذيفة
Abu Hudhayfa was about 30 years old
و"أبو حذيفة" عمره 30 عاماً تقريباً
The sharia official was Abu Hamza al-Tunsi
"كان الشرعي اسمه "أبو حمزة التونسي
There was another man, originally from Sukhna, living on Sajiyah Street in Raqqa
وكان يوجد شخص آخر "سخني" الأصل (أي من مدينة السخنة) من منطقة "شارع الساجية" في مدينة الرقة
Named Abu Zayd
"اسمه "أبو زيد
His brother was the emir of the Islamic Police
وأخوه كان أمير الشرطة الإسلامية
In Raqqa Province, overseeing the whole wilaya
في محافظة الرقة والمسؤول عن الولاية بالكامل
Abu Zayd was a sharia official
و"أبو زيد" شرعي
Second in rank under Abu Hamza al-Tunsi
شرعي في المرتبة الثانية "تحت الشرعي "أبو حمزة التونسي
He worked as a messenger between the court and the Hisba’s sharia office
حيث كان يعمل كمراسل بين المحكمة وبين شرعية الحسبة
As for how many times I was imprisoned
طبعاً بخصوص عدد المرات التي سجنت بها
If I tried to describe my suffering, I’d need 3 months to finish
وإذا أردت التكلم عن حجم معاناتنا سأبقى 3 أشهر أتكلم حتى أتمكن من وصفها
The torture and misery we endured
والعذاب و المأساة التي مرّت علينا
I was imprisoned 28 times
إذ أن عدد المرات التي سجنت بها 28 مرة
Some people might think I’m lying, but the locals know me well
ومن الممكن بعض الأشخاص يقولون عني كاذب ولكن أولاد البلد يعرفونني جيداً
My bag was always ready, because every 2 or 3 days ISIS would arrest me
حيث أصبحت حقيبتي جاهزة في كل يومين أو ثلاثة أعتقل من قبل داعش
The first time I was jailed in a security checkpoint, the charge was suspicion
طبعاً في المرة الأولى سُجنت في نقطة أمنية، وكانت تهمتي الشبهة
I was imprisoned there for 56 days
حيث سُجنت هناك 56 يوماً
The other 27 times were all for cigarette trading
والاعتقالات ال27 مرة كانوا كلهم من أجل تجارة السجائر
My detentions ranged between 10 to 15 days, sometimes up to 2 months
كانت تتراوح مدة اعتقالي بين 10 و15 يوماً وبين الشهرين والشهر ونصف
Then they’d release me, since they found no evidence, and I was very cautious around them
ثم يتم الإفراج عني، كونه لا يوجد عليّ دليل، وأنا كنت على حذر جداً منهم
The last time
طبعاً في آخر مرة
They
حيث أنهم
Launched a campaign against cigarette sellers, and ISIS members specifically targeted me
جاءوا بحملة على بائعي السجائر وتقصدني عناصر التنظيم بالذات
Me and 2 or 3 other people
عليّ وعلى 2 أو 3 أشخاص آخرين
7 people, including me, were sentenced to qisas [execution by retribution]
والذين حكموا معي بالقصاص هم 7 أشخاص
They sentenced them to qisas with me too
حكموا عليهم بالقصاص معي أيضاً
They summoned me and took me by deceit
فاستدعوني إليهم وأخذوني عن طريق الحيلة
They tricked me and took me away
وعندما احتالوا عليّ وأخذوني
They called me on the phone and said, Are you Talal al-Shuweimi? I said, Yes, I am Talal al-Shuweimi
اتصلوا بي علي الهاتف، وقالوا لي: أنت طلال شويمي؟ فقلت لهم : أجل أنا طلال الشويمي
They said, Someone confessed against you
قالوا لي: هناك شخص اعترف عليك
He said you sold him 2 cartons of cigarettes
يقول أنك بعته صندوقين من السجائر
That wasn’t true at all
طبعاً كلامه هذا غير صحيح
Because I hadn’t personally sold cigarettes for about a year
لأنني منذ سنة تقريباً لم أبع السجائر بيدي
Yes, I was a cigarette dealer
أجل أنا كنت تاجر سجائر
But
لكن
When I was in the trade, I didn’t distribute or sell cigarettes myself
عندما كنت تاجر سجائر أنا لا أوزع ولا أبيع السجائر
I didn’t distribute or sell them
لا أوزع ولا أبيع
When they summoned me, I told them, I’ll come right away
وعندما استدعوني، قلت لهم: سآتي في الحال
I got in my car and went to the Hisba, which was at the end of Sajiyah Street
ركبت سيارتي وذهبت إلى الحسبة وموقع الحسبة كان في نهاية شارع الساجية
On Atiya Bakery Street
"بشارع فرن "عطية
And the Hisba emir who was on Sajiyah Street
وأمير الحسبة الذي كان في شارع الساجية
Was named Issa, from the Jais clan, known as Abu Humam
"اسمه "عيسى "من "عشيرة الجيس" ملقب "أبو همام
And Abu Humam, before that
و "أبو همام" سابقاً
Had been a sergeant in the Political Security branch under the Assad regime
كان برتبة مساعد في الأمن السياسي عند نظام الأسد
When he was a sergeant under the Assad regime and ISIS was established
وعندما كان مساعد عند نظام الأسد وتأسست دولة داعش
Abu Humam came and announced his defection and joined the Islamic State
جاء "أبو همام" وأعلن انشقاقه وانضمامه إلى دولة الإسلام
When Abu Humam summoned me, he had already raided my house about 10 times
"عندما استدعاني "أبو همام وكان في السابق داهمني ما يقارب 10 مرات
Out of 27 raids, he came several times, knowing they’d never find cigarettes with me
من ضمن 27 مرة، داهمني أكثر من مرة وهم على معرفة أنهم لن يجدوا لدي سجائر
One time he knocked on my door and called out, “Hey Shuweimi!”
في إحدى المرات طرق عليّ الباب أبو همام" وقال لي منادياً: يا شويمي"
Your hookah is running, and we know you don’t have cigarettes, but bring the hookah and come
أرجيلتُكَ شغّالة ونحن نعرف ليس لديك سجائر، لكن أحضر الأرجيلة وتعال
So I carried the hookah with its coals and placed it in his car
فحملت الأرجيلة بفحمها ووضعتها لديه في السيارة
When Abu Humam summoned me, I asked him, Where’s the man?
"وعندما استدعاني "أبو همام قلت له: أين الرجل؟
Who testified against me? He told me, Rest for 5 minutes
الذي أعترف عليّ فقال لي: استرح 5 دقائق
Now I’ll call the man
والآن سوف أتصل بالرجل
When he called me, he said the man is here with me, come see him
:طبعاً عندما اتصل بي، قال لي أن الرجل موجود عندي هنا، تعال لتراه
When I went, it turned out there was no man there at all
وعندما ذهبت تبيّن أنه لاوجود لرجل لديه! كما قال
He said, In 5 minutes he’ll come
فقال لي: الآن 5 دقائق وسوف يأتيك
So I waited 5 minutes
فانتظرت 5 دقائق
And said, Abu Humam, where’s the man? He told me, You sold cigarettes
وقلت له: يا "أبو همام" أين الرجل؟ قال لي: أنت بعت السجائر
I said, Sheikh
قلت له: يا شيخ
I swore to him by God, and honestly, I swear truthfully, I don’t sell cigarettes
وحلفت له بالله، وبالفعل أنا أحلف بالله بصدق، لأنني لا أبيع السجائر
And I don’t distribute cigarettes. I have workers who sell and deliver instead of me
ولا أوزع السجائر، لدي شغيلة ولدي عمال يبيعون ويوزعون عوضاً عني
What surprised me was his attitude, and I sat down
المهم في الأمر أني تفاجأت من أسلوبه وجلست
I told him, Abu Humam, let me tell you something. Even if I sold two boxes of cigarettes
وقلت له: "أبو همام" أريد أن قول لك شيء، لو أني بعت صندوقين سجائر
You’re not smarter than Abu Seif. If he were in your place, he would’ve arrested me right away
"أنت لست أكثر دهاءً من "أبو سيف لو كان مكانك لاعتقلني مباشرة
The news would’ve reached Abu Seif before it reached you
لوصل الخبر إلى "أبو سيف" قبل أن يأتيك أنت
He said, God willing, and started laughing
قال لي: خيراً إن شاء الله، وبدأ يضحك
They took me to the Investigation Section and up to the second floor
فأخذوني إلى قسم التحري وأصعدوني إلى الطابق العلوي
They brought me into a room on the second floor, where the Investigation Section was located
أدخلوني إلى غرفة في الطابق الثاني كان في هذا الطابق قسم التحري
It was headed by Abu Hamza al-Tunisi, the senior sharia official and overall emir
"الذي كان يترأسه "أبو حمزة التونسي الشرعي الكبير وهو أمير كل شيء
Under him were the Emir of Investigation, Abu Seif Maqs, and Abu Hudhayfa
وتحته أمير التحري "أبو سيف مقص" و"أبو حذيفة"
And Abu Zaid, from the Sakhani clan
"و"أبو زيد" وهو من عشيرة "السخاني
His brother, Fayez, was the Emir of the Islamic Police
وأخوه اسمه "فايز" أمير الشرطة الإسلامية
They took me upstairs
فأخذوني إلى الأعلى
My hands were tied behind my back
وأنا كنت مقيد الأيدي إلى الخلف
And I was blindfolded, and they began beating me
ومعصوب العينين وبدأ الضرب
They hit me with sticks and metal rods , the beating was extremely painful
يضربونني بالعصي والقضبان الحديدية والضرب كان أليماً جداً
I was beaten for 3 days straight
بقيت مدة 3 أيام أتلقى الضرب
They poured water on me and kept beating me again and again
يسكبون عليّ الماء ويضربوني ويسكبون عليّ الماء ويضربوني
When I woke up, I found myself hanging on the wall on the second floor
وعندما صحيت وجدت نفسي معلق على الجدار في الطابق الثاني
That area was at the start of Sajiyah Street, at the intersection with Hittin School Street
تقع هذه المنطقة في أول شارع الساجية عند تقاطع شارع مدرسة حطين مع شارع الساجية
That place was known as the Investigation Zone
من المعروف أن هنا منطقة التحري
I found myself hanging
وجدت نفسي معلق
I remained hanging on the wall for 18 days
بقيت 18 يوماً معّلقاً على الجدار
It was the middle of the hot summer season
ومن الجو الذي كان في فصل الصيف الحار
But our Lord, praise be to Him, is merciful in His mercy
فربّنا سبحانه وتعالى رحيم برحمته
And in His glory and majesty
وعزته وجلالته
The heat actually helped me endure the beatings and pain
فالجو الحار كان يساعدني على تحمل الضرب والألم
When my body was hot and sweating, the blows hurt less than when it was cold in winter
فعندما يكون جسمي حار وساخن وأتلقى الضرب يختلف عندما يكون جسمي بردان في الشتاء
I suffered terribly from thirst
ومرت عليّ مأساة كبيرة من العطش
My toes barely touched the ground
وأصابع قدمي بالكاد تلمس الأرض قليلاً
And I could hardly reach a bottle of drink
وبالكاد أستطيع أن أمسك بعبوة الشراب
I would bring it close when they gave me a break to drink, from the intensity of thirst
وأقربها إليّ عندما يعطوني راحة كي أشربها من شدة العطش
Because of the severe torture
وبسبب العذاب الشديد
Abu Seif wrapped his hand around my beard
لفَّ "أبو سيف" يده على لحيتي
He grabbed my beard,it was long,and dragged me by it while my hands were shackled
لف يده على لحيتي، وكانت لحيتي طويلة وسحبني من لحيتي وأنا مقيد اليدين
I was out of breath, but God Almighty gives a person strength
وكنت بآخر أنفاسي لكن ربنا سبحانه وتعالى يعطي العبد القوة
Great and powerful strength
قوة كبيرة وعظيمة
He kept dragging me by my beard, saying, I’ll teach the whole town a lesson through you
كان يسحبني من لحيتي ويقول لي: سأربي بك كل البلد
He said to me, plainly, “The time of the Prophet is gone”
قال لي: بصريح العبارة "زمن رسول الله ذهب"
I told him, Are we now living in Pharaoh’s time?
قلت له: هل نحن الآن في زمن "فرعون"؟
For you to say the Prophet’s era has passed?
كي تقول أن أيام رسول الله قد ذهبت
He dragged me by my beard until he brought me to the feet of Ibrahim al-Fakkash
أخذني من لحيتي "حتى وصل بي إلى أقدام "إبراهيم الفكّاش
Who was nicknamed al-Bariwi
"الملقب "البرّيوي
He was sentenced along with me too
وكان محكوم معي أيضاً
They told us we’d been sentenced to execution, but the ruling hadn’t been carried out yet
وهنا، قالوا لنا: أنه حكم علينا بالقصاص لكنهم لم يصدروا الحكم علينا بعد
He dragged me by my beard, pulling me along the ground
أخذني من لحيتي مسحوباً على الأرض
Until we reached the feet of Ibrahim al-Fakkash, nicknamed al-Bariwi
"إلى أقدام "إبراهيم الفكّاش" الملقب "البرّيوي
He asked him, Do you know this man?
قال له: هل تعرف هذا الرجل؟
He replied, Yes, I know him
أجابه: أجل، أعرفه
Abu Seif said to al-Bariwi, This is the clever player, al-Shuweimi
"قال "أبو سيف" مخاطباً "البريوي "هذا هو اللاعب الذكي "الشويمي
They called me the clever player because they never caught me with cigarettes
هم يسموني اللاعب الذكي لأنهم لم يُمسكوا بحوزتي سجائر
I’d been in so many prisons and detentions,arrested 27 times before by the Hisba (religious police)
ولكثرة السجون والاعتقالات ولأني اعتقلت 27 مرة من قبل الحسبة
Once they detained me for security reasons, and another time I spent a month and a half in Point 11
ومرةً اعتقلوني أمنياً ومرةً أخرى سجنت مدة شهر ونصف في النقطة 11
That’s why they gave me that nickname
فأطلقوا عليّ هذا الاسم
He dragged me by my beard all that distance, pulled me out of the room again, still dragging me
سحبني من لحيتي كل هذه المسافة وأخرجني من الغرفة مرة أخرى وسحبني
I stayed with them in the investigation section for about 53 or 54 days
بقيت لديهم في التحري ما يقارب 53 يوماً أو 54 يوماً
They came
جاءوا
And shackled my hands behind my back again
وقيدوني من يدي مرة أخرى للخلف
They took me out after 53 days
وأخرجوني بعد 53 يوماً
And said to me
:وقالوا لي
We’ll spare your neck if you pay a sum of money
سنعتق رقبتك، إذا دفعت مبلغ مالي
In exchange for paying a financial amount
مقابل دفعك مبلغ مالياً
The ruling would be treated like theft but under a religious ruling
ويصبح الحكم كالسرقة ولكن بفتوة دينية
In the past, people would say things like, I’ll rob you right before your eyes
في السابق يوجد أشخاص يقولون مثلاً: أسرقك أمام نظر عينيك
My strength and my dignity
قوتك ومروءتي
They wanted to rob me, but in the name of what the Prophet said,meaning freeing a slave
ويريدون نهبي، لكن من باب قال رسول الله بمعنى عتق رقبة
They asked me, What property do you have? At that time, I owned 6 or 7 cars
سألوني: ما لديك من أملاك؟ كنت أملك حينها 6 أو 7 سيارات
Because I worked hard in the cigarette trade
لأني عملت بتجارة السجائر بجد وكفاح
Whether that work was forbidden or not
وطبعاً yن كان العمل هذا حرام أو لا
Some people said it was forbidden, others said it wasn’t
أشخاص قالوا أنه عمل محرم وأشخاص قالوا ليس محرم
Maybe we were ignorant about it, but we didn’t really know whether it was forbidden or not
من الممكن أنه كان لدينا جهل بذلك ولكن لم نكن نعرف أنه عمل محرم أو لا
The important thing is, I worked hard, forbidden or not
المهم في الأمر أنني تعبت سواء كان محرم أو لا
I struggled and earned that money
تعبت وحصلت على المال
They took everything I had,gold, silver, and cars
فأخذوا كل شيء لديّ من ليرات ذهب وفضة وسيارات
They took everything, even my farmland
واخذوا كل شيء، حتى كان لديّ أرض زراعية
I had a deed of ownership from 50 years ago
ولديّ سند تمليك بها منذ 50 سنة
In my name, inherited from my father
باسمي ورثتها من أبي
Back then, the Syrian regime used to seize land from people who owned a lot of it
لأن النظام السوري بالسابق كان يأخذ الأراضي من الذين يمتلكون أرHضي كثيرة
Out of fear, my father registered the land in his sons’ names
ومن خوف أبي على الأرض سجل ملكيتها بأسماء أبناءه
He divided the land equally among his sons
ووزع الأراضي بالتساوي على أبناءه
So my share was the same as my brothers’
فكان نصيبي كنصيب إخوتي
Even the land that was originally my father’s
حتى أرضي التي تعود ملكيتها لأبي
They made me fingerprint it as sold and bought
بصموني على الأرض بيع وشراء
I also had a motorbike with two frames at times
وكان لديّ دراجة نارية مكونة من إطارين في بعض الأحيان
I used it around the neighborhood and inside the city during traffic jams and hot weather
كنت أستخدمها في الحي وداخل المدينة عند أزمات المرور والجو الحار
They made me fingerprint that as sold and bought too
بصّموني عليه بيع وشراء أيضاً
I was detained many times, and regarding the interrogation sessions
اعتُقلت مرات كثيرة وبالنسبة لجلسات التحقيق
They sometimes lasted long, sometimes they interrogated me, sometimes they didn’t
كانت مدتها طويلة أحياناً يحققون معي وأحياناً لا
Just to put psychological pressure on me
فقط للضغط عليّ نفسياً
My first interrogation was at Point 11
أول تحقيق معي كان في النقطة 11
I talked too much during the interrogation because of how unjustly they treated me
كنت من كثرة كلامي داخل التحقيق بسبب ظلمهم ليّ
I was innocent,I was just trying to earn a living, working as a taxi driver
أنا شخص لا يوجد عليّ شيء، وأنا شخص كنت أترزق الله، حيث كنت سائق سيارة أجرة
Because I talked so much, they interrogated me and took me to the judge
ومن كثرة كلامي معهم حققوا معي وعرضوني على القاضي
Their system was that every week they brought us a blank sheet
كان نظامهم في كل أسبوع يحضرون لنا ورقة بيضاء
We’d write our names, like Talal Mustafa al-Shuweimi
لنسجل عليها أسماءنا مثلاً "طلال مصطفى الشويمي"
Was he interrogated? If yes, he should write “yes”
هل تم التحقيق معه؟ وإذا تم "التحقيق معه، يجب عليه أن يكتب "نعم
If not interrogated, he should write “no”
وإذا لم يتم التحقيق معه "يجب أن يكتب كلمة "لا
And was he presented to the judge? “Yes” or “no”
"وهل تم عرضه على القاضي؟ "نعم" أو "لا
And every time, I wrote “no,” blaming them for my case
"وأنا في كل مرة كنت أكتب فيها "لا وحملهم في هذه القضية
Since I had children, no means, and my house was rented in the beginning
كوني لديّ أطفال وليس لديّ حيلة ومنزلي كان في الإيجار في بدايتي
Sometimes they’d take me to the prison corridor
وفي بعض الأحيان كانوا يأخذوني إلى ممر السجن
At Point 11
في النقطة 11
They’d leave me for two or three hours, blindfolded
يأخذوني مدة ساعتين أو ثلاثة وأنا معصوب العينين
Standing on my feet
واقفاً على قدمي
Or sitting on the ground
أو جالساً على الأرض
They wouldn’t speak to me or beat me
وكانوا لا يتكلمون معي شيئاً ولا يضربوني
But I could hear the sounds of torture and beatings in the corridor
حيث كنت أسمع بعض أصوات التعذيب والضرب في ممر السجن
They’d shout at the prisoners, Stand up, you dog! Turn around! Lift your foot! They had their own methods of torture
هم يقولون للسجناء قف يا وغد واستدر للخلف وارفع قدمك، ولهم أساليبهم الخاصة في التعذيب
But they didn’t beat me, they just kept me in the corridor blindfolded
لكنهم لم يضربوني فقط كانوا يضعوني في ممر السجن معصوب العينين
Leaving me that way for two or three hours
ويبقوني لمدة ساعتين أو ثلاثة على هذا الشكل
In the end, he’d say to me, Sheikh
في آخر الأمر، يقول لي: يا شيخ
Go back to your group cell. I’d remove the blindfold inside and hand it to him through the window
اذهب إلى مهجعك، فأفك العصبة القماشية داخل المهجع وأعطيه إياها من خلال النافذة
That happened about 10 times
تكررت هذه الحالة معي ما يقارب 10 مرات
And the last time
وفي آخر مرة
I told them I wanted to be interrogated because I was honestly afraid they’d put me in the corridor again
قلت لهم: أريد أن يحقق معي خشيةً من أن يضعوني في الممر بصراحة
And one time
وفي إحدى المرات
I lost my patience
نفذ صبري
I started crying and said, It’s only one death
فبدأت بالبكاء، وقلت هي موتة واحدة
A person only dies once
والإنسان كم مرة سيموت
I started crying and shouting, so they blindfolded me and took me away
بدأت بالبكاء والصراخ، فعصبوا عيني وأخذوني
They took me to the interrogation room
حيث أخذوني إلى غرفة التحقيق
And the interrogator
والمحقق
He died, may God have mercy on him
مات طبعاً ولا نستطيع القول غير رحمه الله
His name was Abu Abdul Rahman
"كان اسمه "أبو عبد الرحمن
He was from the Jaif area in Raqqa, from the Ghanem al-Zahir clan
" من منطقة "الجايف "في مدينة الرقة من عشيرة "الغانم الظاهر
He said to me, Talal al-Shuweimi
"فقال لي: "طلال الشويمي
You
أنت
Are you still doing amulet sorcery?
هل مازلتم تعملون سحر الأحجبة؟
Since I’m from the Marandiyya clan, and our ancestors were known for religion and for using drums
"كوني أنا من عشيرة "المرندية وفي السابق كانوا أجدادنا أهل دين وأهل دف
He said, Do you still make amulet spells and play the drums?
فقال لي: أما زلتم تصنعون سحر الأحجبة؟ وتضربون على الدف؟
And I knew him. I knew him well
وأنا أعرفه، وأعرفه جيداً
I told him, I swear, Sheikh
قلت له: والله يا شيخ
I told him these words when you stop playing the rababa [string instrument]
فقلت له هذا الكلام عندما تتركون العزف على الربابة
He said to me, Are you the brother of Abdul Rahim Shuweimi?
قال لي: هل أنت أخو فلان "عبد الرحيم شويمي"
I said, Yes, I’m his brother
قلت له: أجل، أنا أخوه
I said, But, Sheikh
قلت له: ولكن يا شيخ
At that time, my family was trying to use mediations for me
وهنا عائلتي كانوا يحضرون لي الوساطات
My mother, an old woman, wherever she saw a clan sheikh or a member of ISIS
وأمي امرأة عجوز أين ما كانت ترى شيخ عشيرة أو شخص من داعش
Any man with a long beard, she would go to him and say, My son has children, and so on
وكل شخص ذو لحية طويلة تذهب إليه وتقول له: ولدي لديه أطفال وهكذا
She would follow them around for her son, hoping they’d release me, and I had children
تتبعهم من أجل ابنها لعلهم يخرجوني، وأنا لدي أطفال
My children became my parents’ responsibility, and they had no power to help
أصبح أبنائي أمانة في رقبة أمي وأبي ولا حول ولا قوة لهم
We argued about this topic
فتجادلنا حول هذا الكلام
Then he said to me, You’re a filthy person
عندها، قال لي: أنت شخص وسخ
I said, So now for you the Muslim is filthy, and Muslims deserve execution
فقلت له: اليوم أصبح لديكم المسلم وسخ وأصبح المسلمون للقصاص
It’s the rule of the strong over the weak, and there’s no power or strength
طبعاً حكم القوي على الضعيف ولا حول ولا قوة
He said to me, God willing, you won’t leave this place
قال لي: إن شاء الله لن تخرج من هنا
He brought in a man, and that man
أحضر شخص وهذا الشخص
Had a medium-sized passenger van
كان لديه سيارة نقل ركاب متوسطة الحجم
His house was in the Kalta area in Raqqa’s countryside, and he used to transport female teachers
"يقع منزله في منطقة "الكالطة في ريف الرقة، وكان ينقل معلمات المدارس
The group forced teachers to attend repentance courses. The point is, he used to drive those teachers
وقد فرض التنظيم على المعلمين دورات استتابة المهم في الأمر أنه كان ينقل المعلمات معه
The group accused him of smuggling people out of Raqqa
فاعتبر التنظيم أنه يهرب الناس إلى خارج الرقة
They brought the man and blindfolded him
أحضروا الشخص، وعصبوا عينيه
That act was meant as punishment for me
وهذا العمل كان بمثابة تأديب لي
I felt it was a punishment for me, and while he was talking to me
شعرتها بمثابة تأديب لي وأثناء مناقشته لي
He made me sit on a chair
أجلسني على الكرسي
While I was blindfolded
وأنا معصوب الأعين
I was only blindfolded and tied with plastic ties
كنت معصوب الأعين فقط ومقيد بواسطة أربطة بلاستيكية
The kind used for bundling electric cables
تستخدم في حزم أشرطة الكهرباء
Then he brought the man and started beating him with a water hose called “Lakhdar Brahimi”
فأحضر الرجل، وبدأ يضربه بخرطوم مياه قاسِ " يطلقون عليه اسم "الأخضر الإبراهيمي
He disfigured the man’s body with the beating
حيث أنه شوه جسد الرجل ضرباً
The man cried intensely
ومن شدة بكاء الرجل
I could hear the hose striking near me, and he kept beating him until he killed him
وصوت الخرطوم يمر بقربي واستمر بضربه إلى أن موته ضرباً
Finally, I was so upset that I said, He’ll kill this man if he continues
في الآخر من شدة انزعاجي سيقتل الرجل إن بقي هكذا
I told him, I don’t want the interrogation anymore, just stop hitting him, because I realized he was doing it for my sake
قلت له: أنا لم أعد أريد التحقيق، فقط أترك الرجل، لأني أدركت أنه يتصرف هكذا من أجلي
He couldn’t hit me, not out of fear
لا يستطيع أن يضربني ليس خوفاً مني
But because there was no proof against me, so he had no right to beat me
ولكن لعدم وجود إثبات عليّ حيث لا يحق له أن يضربني
And because Abu Yousuf the interrogator and Abu Suhaib the Tunisian were above him in rank
"وبسبب وجود "أبو يوسف تحقيق و "أبو صهيب التونسي" أعلى منه مرتبةَ
Although Abu Suhaib the Tunisian was very strict religiously, he never allowed anyone to be beaten
"صحيح أن "أبو صهيب التونسي متشدد بالدين لكنه لا يسمح بضرب أحد
Those who conducted the interrogations with us
والذي كان يتولى التحقيق معنا
Were from inside the prison
هم من داخل السجن
Like Abu Yousuf the interrogator and Abu Abdul Rahman
"مثل "أبو يوسف تحقيق" و "أبو عبد الرحمن
The second one was from the al-Sahou clan
"وهذا الشخص الثاني من عشيرة "السهو
The group deliberately used people in interrogations who had strong intelligence connections inside the city
بحيث يتعمد التنظيم في التحقيق، على التحري والأمنيات القوية لديهم داخل البلد
That’s one point, and the first and most important
هذه نقطة والنقطة الأولى والأهم
The most important and strongest thing they had
الأهم والأقوى لديهم
Was that they had security agents inside the prison
هي أن لديهم أمنيين داخل السجن
They had security agents from our own people, from our towns, sadly
لديهم أمنيين من شعبنا أبناء البلد للأسف الشديد
ISIS had security agents from our local people working inside the prison for money
يوجد للتنظيم أمنيين من أبناء بلدنا داخل السجن يعملون معهم مقابل المال
For example, someone would come, and I’d look at him, and one of them
مثلاً يأتي وأنظر إليه ومن إحدى هذه الشخصيات
Was from the al-Bou Saraya clan, named Abdullah
"من عشيرة "البو سرايا" شخص اسمه "عبد الله
He sat beside me, and I had been in prison for 10 days
جلس بجواري، وكان لي 10 أيام في السجن
When he sat and started crying, saying he was wronged and jailed over selling a pistol
عندما جلس وبدأ بالبكاء ويقول أنه مظلوم وسُجن من أجل بيعة مسدس
I trusted him, as I had nothing to hide
وثقت بهذا الشخص وأنا لا يوجد لديّ شيء لأقوله
The group’s informants or security men
فيحاول مخبرو أو أمنيو التنظيم
Would come acting like victims, saying they were innocent, and talk about ISIS in front of me, saying we’ll get out tomorrow
أن يأتوا بأسلوب المظلوم، وأنه ليس عليه شيء ويتكلم عن التنظيم أمامي، وغداً سنخرج من هنا
And say, God is generous, and promise that such-and-such faction would enter the city
والله كريم ويتوعد بدخول الفصيل الفلاني المدينة
So the person in front of them would confess and start talking
لكي يعترف الشخص الذي أمامه ويتحدث له
These were the ones ISIS sent in as informants and internal agents
هؤلاء الذين يدخلونهم كأمنين ومخبرين للتنظيم
They were very intelligent people
شخصيات ذكية جداً
One of these people was named Abdullah al-Asaad
"إحدى هذه الشخصيات اسمه "عبد الله الأسعد
His house was next to the Nabhan Glass Shop in Raqqa, and he was killed
ومنزله يقع بجوار متجر زجاج النبهان في مدينة الرقة وقد قُتل
While fighting in one of the battles
وهو يقاتل في إحدى المعارك
He started crying in front of me, and about 40 days later
بدأ بالبكاء أمامي وإحدى المرّات بعد ما يقارب 40 يوماً
He started crying again and told me that his mother had died
بدأ بالبكاء، وقال لي: أن أمه توفيت
When I got out of prison, his goal was to get information from me
وعندما خرجت من السجن كانت غايته كسب المعلومات مني
When I was released, I went to his house to offer condolences to his father
عندما خرجت من السجن ذهبت إلى منزله لكي أعزي والده
And I said, Keep your faith strong, Abdullah is crying and mourning his mother
ولقول: سلم دينكم وإيمانكم وأن "عبد الله" يبكي وحزين على فراق والدته
Since I had been released, it was my duty to visit my friend’s family who was still in prison
كوني خرجت من السجن فيتوجب عليّ الذهاب لزيارة عائلة صديقي الذي في السجن
I was shocked when his mother came out, cursing him and saying, May God never grant him success, and that she had disowned him
فتفاجأت بخروج والدته، وهي تدعو عليه وتقول لا وفقه الله، وإنها تبرأت منه
She said, He claims I’m dead, but he’s an informant for the group
يقول أنني توفيت، وهو مخبر للتنظيم
There were many people who infiltrated others in this same way
ويوجد كثير أشخاص يخترقون الأشخاص الذين أمامهم بهذا الشكل
Our people are kind-hearted and simple
وشعبنا مسكين وطيب القلب
So they might slip and say something by mistake, and that security informant
فيزلق لسانه بكلمة عن طريق الخطأ فيقوم المخبر الأمني هذا
Would then
فيقوم
Report it to the security forces, and based on that, the person would be accused. Many people were killed that way
بنقلها للأمنين، وعلى هذا الأساس يلصقون التهمة بالشخص، وكثير من الناس قُتلوا هكذا
Stories like this were common
مثل وأمثال هذا الحديث
As for torture methods
بالنسبة لوسائل التعذيب
Torture
التعذيب
We witnessed how they tortured people
وكنا نرى تعذيبهم
The problem was that they had two styles
المشكلة أن لديهم أسلوبين
One underground
أسلوب تحت الأرض بشكل
And another above ground, completely different
وأسلوب فوق الأرض بشكل مختلف
Like a person with two faces,and both faces were terrifying
مثل الشخص الذي لديه وجهان والشخص الذي لديه وجهان مخيف
As for the Hisba (religious police)
وبالنسبة للحسبة
It had 20 faces
لديها 20 وجه
Regarding torture methods
بالنسبة لأساليب التعذيب
Anything you can imagine existed. Many locals were imprisoned
كل شيء يخطر على عقولكم بالتأكيد يوجد الكثير من أبناء البلد سجنوا
And subjected to different torture methods,for example, crucifixion
وتعرضوا لأساليب التعذيب ومن هذه الأساليب مثلاً الصلب
Or they’d shackle your hands like this with cuffs
ومثلاً يقيد يديك بهذا الشكل بالأصفاد
When your hands were raised with the cuffs, your ribs would tear apart from here
ومثلاً عندما تقيّد اليدين بالأصفاد وترفع للأعلى تتمزق الأضلع من هنا
When Abu Seif lifted the prisoner,he was a huge man from eating too much Western food
فعندما يرفع "أبو سيف" السجين للأعلى حيث أنه ذو جسم ضخم، من كثرة تناوله للوجبات الغربية
God gave him the strength to eat 4 or 5 sandwiches
الله أعطاه العافية ليأكل 4 أو 5 سندويشات
At the expense of the so-called caliphate
على حساب الخلافة
He was very strong, while I was weak
وكان ذو حيل قوي، وأنا كنت ضعيف
He would grab me by the neck and lift me about 20 or 30 centimeters off the ground
فكان يحملني من عنقي ويرفعني بين 20 و30 سم تقريباً عن الأرض
My legs would kick violently, just like in American movies
وقدمي تتحرك بشدة بالفعل مثل الأفلام الأميركية
I couldn’t walk or breathe from the pain in my chest
قدمي لا أستطيع المشي عليها ولا أستطيع التنفس من ألم صدري
I had tonsillitis, my ribs were broken, and to this day I still suffer chest pain
كان لدي التهاب في اللوزتين وأضلعي متكسرة وإلى الآن أعاني من ألم في ضلوع صدري
At that time
وفي ذات الوقت
The guys, God bless them, took care of me for about 68 days
الشباب جزاهم الله خير بقوا يرعوني ما يقارب 68 يوماً
They would take me to the toilets, bathe me, and cared for me well
مثلاً يأخذوني إلى دورات المياه ويحمموني، اعتنوا بي جيداً
Among them were Ibrahim Abu Nashwa and Ibrahim Ayyoub, known as Shantar
"ومنهم "إبراهيم أبو نشوى "و "إبراهيم أيوب" الملقب "شنتر
All the guys who were with me in prison were kind and helped me in every way
وجميع الشباب الذين كانوا برفقتي في السجن طيبين وساعدوني على أكمل وجه
I was never cared for in my life the way those six men cared for me when I was the seventh
ولم أُعزّ حقيقةً في حياتي مثلما كانوا الشباب الستة يعتنون بي وأنا الشخص السابع
When I was broken and my ribs were shattered in prison
عندما كنت مكسر وأضلعي مكسرة في السجن
Out of fear and terror
نحن من الخوف والرعب
My ribs and legs could barely move
وكانت ضلوعي لا تساعدني على الحركة ولا حتى قدمي
In the room above us there were solitary cells, each about one square meter, with a ceiling
فكان يوجد لدينا داخل الغرفة في الأعلى منفردات مساحتها متر مربع ولها من الأعلى سقف
Barriwi carried me and we went up
حملني "البرّيوي" وصعدنا إلى الأعلى
He broke a small iron piece from one of the solitary cells
فوجدنا قطعة حديدية صغيرة كسرها "البريوي" من إحدى المنفردات
Then Barriwi started scraping the wall
وهنا بدأ "البريوي" بحك الجدار
The wall was coated with smooth cement
والجدار كان مغطى بالصين الإسمنتي الناعم
We discovered it was made of modern white stone, not black stone
عندها تبين لنا أنه مكون من الحجر الأبيض الحديث وليس من الأسود
Barriwi said, “Talal al-Shuweimi, let’s escape,” so we tried to run away
:فقال "البريوي" لي طلال شويمي" هيا بنا لنهرب، فخرجنا لنهرب"
It was me and Barriwi
"أنا و"البريوي
And Ibrahim Ayyoub, known as Shantar, was watching the door with Bara al-Ano
"و "إبراهيم أيوب" الملقب "شنتر "كان يراقب لنا الباب، هو و "براء العنو
We started digging the wall and dug the length of about two bricks and the width of two more
بدأنا بحفر الجدار فحفرنا ما يقارب طول حجرتين بناء وعرض حجرتين أيضاً
But we were terrified, because each brick
لكن من الخوف والذعر، حيث أن الحجرة الواحدة
Had two sides, one of them thick
لها جهتين، أحدها سميك
The thick side was pressed against another thick side, with a cement layer in between that couldn’t be broken easily,it made a loud sound
بحيث أن الجهة السميكة ملاصقة للجهة السميكة الأخرى وبينهم يوجد طبقة إسمنتية لا تكسر بالقطعة الحديدية بسهولة وتصدر صوتاً عالياً
Across from our room, one of the group’s members was standing guard
ويوجد مقابل غرفتنا شخص يحرسنا من عناصر التنظيم
We were terrified
كنا نخاف
I went to the sheikh and told him, Out of fear, no one knows what to do,especially the sentenced ones
جئت وقلت للشيخ، أي شخص من الفزع والخوف لا يعرف ماذا يتصرف خاصة إن كان محكوماً
So I said to the imprisoned sheikh with us
فجئت وقلت للشيخ المسجون معنا
My brother
يا أخي أنت
Read to us from the Quran, maybe God will save us from them and help us escape
اقرأ لنا من القرآن قليلاً عسى الله أن ينجينا منهم ونستطيع الهروب
Or make them blind to us,things like that, which are close to sorcery, God forbid
أو يكف الله بصرهم عنا، ومن هذه الأشياء وحاشى الله والتي تعد نوعاً من الشعوذة
But we were desperate, and a drowning man clings to a straw
ولكن على أمل والغريق يتعلق بقشة
As you know, I was sentenced to execution, and a drowning man clings not just to a straw but to the water itself
كما تعرفون أنا كنت محكوم بالقصاص والغريق يتعلق بالماء وليس بقشة فقط
Trying to hold onto the water
يحاول التعلق بالماء
The sheikh actually believed himself
والشيخ هذا صدق نفسه
He was a man whose house was on Mansour Street in Raqqa, sentenced to execution
"وهو شخص منزله يقع في "شارع المنصور في مدينة الرقة وحكموا عليه بالقصاص
On charges of sorcery
بتهمة الشعوذة
He said he treated people with traditional Arabic medicine
وعلى قوله أنه كان يعالج الناس بطب العرب
He went to treat a woman who had joint pain in her legs
وذهبت إلى امرأة مفاصل قدميها تؤلمها
And they arrested him for that, accusing him of witchcraft
لكي أعالجها بطب العرب فاعتقلوني على أساس أني مشعوذ
That man started reciting
بدأ هذا الرجل بالقراءة
And it became like some satanic ritual, while we continued pounding on the wall
فأصبح الوضع مثل شعوذة شيطانية وبالفعل بدأنا بطرق الجدار
Hard, but the guard outside didn’t hear us
بقوة ولم يسمعنا الحارس الذي في الخارج
The guard sitting outside was an ISIS member who had just finished his training course
ولم يسمعنا الحارس الذي يجلس في الخارج وهو عنصر في التنظيم تخرج من الدورة حديثاً
His name was Abu al-Yaman
"اسمه "أبو اليمان
Abu al-Yaman was from Aleppo Province
و "أبو اليمان" هذا، أصله حلبي من محافظة حلب
When we made an opening in the wall, one of us, a diabetic man
وعندما حفرنا منفذاً في الجدار كان يوجد معنا أحد الأشخاص مريض السكر
Named Ibrahim al-Ali al-Alkan, known as Abu Nashwa
"واسمه "إبراهيم العلكان" الملقب "أبو نشوى
Got so scared that his blood sugar spiked
والرجل من خوفه ارتفع معه السكر
He almost died
وكاد أن يموت
And he actually did die
مات نهائياً
They had brought us wool blankets
وكانوا أحضروا لنا أغطية من الصوف
Because winter was approaching
إذ اقترب مجيء الشتاء
We tore up those wool blankets, and also some other covers
فمزقنا الأغطية الصوفية التي جلبوها لنا ويوجد بطانيات مزقناها أيضاً
When we broke through the wall of the Hisba prison, behind it was an investigation building on Sajiyah Street
لأنه عندما ثقبنا الجدار في سجن الحسبة كان خلفه مباشرة بناء للتحري في شارع الساجية
There was a depth of about 7 meters
ويوجد عمق ما يقارب 7 أمتار
After 7 meters, there was the yard of a ground-floor house
وبعد عمق 7 أمتار تصل حديقة منزل أرضي
Because of the pounding noise, the homeowner came out
وهنا بسبب صوت الطرق خرج صاحب المنزل على الصوت
He shouted, Who are you? I said, Uncle, I’m Talal al-Shuweimi, your relative
:وبدأ يسأل من أنتم من أنتم؟ فقلت له يا عمي أنا "طلال الشويمي" وأنا قريبك
And Ibrahim al-Fakkash said, I’m from the Fakkash family, from the Shibli Salamah clan
و "إبراهيم الفكّاش" يقول له: أنا "من بيت "الفكاش" من عشيرة "الشبلي السلامة
We started crying and begged him not to report us,we were sentenced to execution
وبدأنا بالبكاء أمامه ونقول له يا عم لا تخبر علينا نحن محكومون بالقصاص
The man cried along with us
بكى الرجل على بكاءنا
He started crying and said, My nephews, jump down quickly
:بدأ البكاء، وقال يا أولاد أخي قفزوا إليّ بسرعة
So they wouldn’t cut off my neck with yours
لكي لا يقصوا عنقي معكم
And the man was holding a laser lighter for us
وكان الرجل يحمل لنا ضوء ولاعة ليزري
He looked at us and said, “My brothers’ sons, hurry up, the daylight has broken,” and when we finished
وينظر إلينا، ويقول: يا أولاد أخي أسرعوا قد أشرق ضوء النهار، وعندما انتهينا
Ibrahim al-Alkan fell ill
"وقد مرض "إبراهيم العلكان
And the last time we went out
وآخر خروجنا
The house of Emir Abu Seif was on Sajiyah Street
وموقع منزل الأمير "أبو سيف" في شارع الساجية
The Hisba (religious police) base was on Sajiyah Street, and the road was like this
والحسبة تقع بشارع الساجية والطريق كان بهذا الشكل
Sajiyah Street is on the southern side
وشارع الساجية يقع في الجهة الجنوبية
The Hisba is on the northern side, and Abu Seif’s house is on Sajiyah Street
والحسبة من الجهة الشمالية ومنزل "أبو سيف" في شارع الساجية
The organization had taken that house from a Kurdish family
وكان التنظيم قد أخذ هذا المنزل من عائلة كردية الأصل
The owner was called Abu Sateef, a well-known bicycle repairman in Raqqa and on Sajiyah Street
وصاحب المنزل يدعى "أبو صطيف" مصلح الدراجات الهوائية معروف في الرقة وفي شارع الساجية
So Abu Seif took his house
"فأخذ منزله "أبو سيف
Abu Seif, the Emir of the Investigation, took the house of Abu Sateef, the Kurdish bicycle repairman
أبو سيف" أمير التحري كان " أخذ منزل "أبو صطيف" الكردي مصلح الدرجات
The Hisba base was across from his house, and when he went out
ومركز الحسبة يقع مقابل منزله، فعندما خرج
He saw that the wall had been destroyed across the width of about two and a half rooms
رأى أن الجدار قد هدم بعرض حجرتين بناء ونصف تقريباً
Suddenly, the security men surrounded the area and came up to us
ولم نشعر إلا أن الأمنيين قد طوقوا المنطقة وصعدوا إلينا
They started shooting at my feet and separated me from the other young men
وبدءوا بإطلاق الرصاص تحت قدمي وفرقوني عن باقي الشباب
Then they brought us back again
وأعادونا من جديد
For the case of crucifixion and suspension, and of course the beatings and insults
على قضية الصلب والتعليق وقضية الضرب والإهانات طبعاً
I was tortured and kept being tortured for 3 more days
تعذبت وبقيت أتعذب لمدة 3 أيام أخرى
After 3 days, they took me to the court
وبعد 3 أيام، أخذوني إلى المحكمة
There was an air fan in the room where they put us
فكان يوجد مروحة هوائية في الغرفة التي وضعونا فيها
It was installed in the wall for air and odor ventilation, called the sharaq [door vent]
التي يضعونها في الجدار "من أجل التنفس وسحب الروائح تدعى "الشراق
I told the guys, “Listen, guys
فقلت للشباب: يا شباب
If they take us down to the same room
إذا أنزلونا إلى نفس الغرفة
The sharaq switch is below, and we’re placed upstairs in the solitary cells
زر تشغيل "الشراق" في الأسفل ونحن وضعونا فوق في المنفردات
When you turn on the metal sharaq, it will make noise
وعندما تشغلون الشراق الحديدي سيصدر ضجيجاً
Whoever among you goes down to our old room, turn it on so we know who was sent there”
والذي ينزل منكم إلى غرفتنا القديمة يشغل الشراق حتى نعرف أن فلان نزل إليها
The first one they summoned was al-Bariwi
"وأول ما استدعوا "البريوي
We waited 5 minutes, 15 minutes, half an hour, and the sharaq still didn’t turn on
انتظرنا 5 دقائق وربع ساعة ونصف ساعة، لم يعمل "الشراق" بعد
Then they summoned another person too
ومن ثم استدعوا شخص أخر أيضاً
And the sharaq still didn’t turn on
ولم يعمل "الشراق" كذلك
Fear and terror spread among us
فدبّ الرعب والخوف فينا
Then they called my name, Talal al-Shuweimi
"نادوا اسمي "طلال شويمي
They shackled me and blindfolded me. Abu Seif lifted me by my shoulder and led me
قيدوني وعصبوا عيني حملني "أبو سيف" من أسفل كتفي وقادوني
And Abu Hudhayfa held me by the other shoulder
و "أبو حذيفة" من أسفل كتفي الأخر
They carried me forcefully as if they were about to carry out the sentence against me and took me out
حملوني بقوة وكأنهم يريدون تنفيذ الحكم عليّ وأخرجوني
They said, “Stand,” so I stood
قالوا لي: قف، فوقفت
He asked me, “Are you so-and-so?” I said, “Yes, I am”
قال لي: أنت فلان الفلان قلت له: أجل أنا
He said, “You did this and that.” I said, “Yes, Sheikh, I was the biggest cigarette trader
فقال لي: أنت فعلت كذا وكذا قلت له: أجل يا شيخ أنا كنت أكبر تاجر سجائر
Under the caliphate, but God guided me, and I quit over a year or a year and a half ago”
في ظل الخلافة، وتاب الله عليّ، وليّ سنة أو سنة ونصف متوقف عن تجارة السجائر
“And now, after I quit the trade, you summon me and treat me like this?”
واليوم بعدما توقفت عن التجارة تستدعوني وتفعلون بي هكذا
We argued, and the sheikh started insulting me
فتجادلنا وبدأ الشيخ بإهانتي
He said, “You’re talkative and loud. You think religion is a game,” and so on
قال لي: أنت ثرثار وكثير الكلام أنت تظن أن الدين لعبة وإلى آخره
He said, “You and that woman,I won’t mention her name,
فقال: أنت وصديقتك فلانة، لا أريد ذكر اسمها
You both smoke hookah and walk around with that other woman”
أنت وهي تشربون الأرجيلة، وتمشون مع فلانة
They were all women suffering from poverty and hunger
طبعاً هم جميعهم نساء من الفقر والجوع
They traded cigarettes to earn a living and support their children
يعملنَّ بتجارة السجائر لأجل رزقة أطفالهم وإعالتهم
Some were widows, others had children, and one had a disabled child
طبعاً بعضهم أرامل وبعضهم لديهم أطفال وإحداهن لديها طفل معاق
They relied on God and borrowed cigarettes from me
يسترزقون الله ويستلفون السجائر مني
To sell them, cover their expenses, and provide for their families
حتى يبيعوهم ويصرفون على نفسهم ويأمنوا معيشتهم
So I said to him, “Sheikh
فقلت له: يا شيخ
You’re accusing me of false charges
أنت بدأت باتهامي بتهم باطلة
Keep the cigarette charge, it’s better than accusing me of adultery
أبقينا على تهمة السجائر أفضل من أن تدخلني بتهمة الزنا
Imagine, I entered prison for cigarette trading and ended up with 10 other charges I had nothing to do with
تخيلوا أنا دخلت السجن بقضية تجارة السجائر فدخلت بعشرة قضايا أخرى ليس ليّ ذنب بها
And sadly, I didn’t even know about them until the very end
وللأسف الشديد لم أعلم بها إلا في نهاية الأمر
In the end, I learned that the cases I was sentenced for had nothing to do with cigarettes
في النهاية حتى علمت أن القضايا التي حكمت لأجلها ليس لها علاقة بتجارة السجائر
My arrest and interrogation were indeed for cigarette trading
بداية استدعائي واعتقالي صحيح لأجل تجارة السجائر
But eventually, none of the charges were related to that
ولكن في آخر الأمر كل القضايا ليست لها علاقة بتجارة السجائر
Even in the same court, they accused me of adultery
وفي نفس المحكمة وجّهوا إليّ اتهام الزنا
With one of the women who sold cigarettes
مع واحدة من النساء التي تبيع السجائر
Now tell me, does it make sense? I have 3 wives, my daughters are unmarried, and I have 13 children
واليوم أنا هل يعقل يا ترى لدي 3 نساء و بناتي عازبات و 13 طفل
And now I’m going to commit adultery?
!واليوم أريد أن أزني
After 3 wives and after reaching 40 or 45 years old?
بعد 3 نساء وبعد عمر 40 و 45 عاماً
I told him, “Sheikh, that’s not logical
قلت له: يا شيخ هذا ليس منطقاً
Leave me with the cigarette trading charge, may God guide you
فتركني وفقك الله بقضية تجارة السجائر
Judge me for that,it’s better than judging me for adultery”
وحاكمني بتجارة السجائر أفضل من أن تحاكمني بالزنا
I told him, “If you don’t fear God, then you should be feared.” He said, “Do you think we don’t fear God?”
قلت له: الذي لا يخاف الله يجب أن تخاف منه قال لي: هل نحن لا نخاف الله؟
Then he stood up and hit me. I don’t know with what, because I was blindfolded
فنهض وضربني، طبعاً لا أعرف بماذا ضربني لأنني كنت معصوب العينين
I felt something running down my head, like heat
شعرت بشيء سال من رأسي، مثل الحرارة
And that’s when he pronounced the sentence
وهنا عندما نطق بالحكم
He didn’t give me anything, didn’t even let me sit. He just asked me a few harsh questions
طبعاً لم يعطيني شيء ولا حتى أجلسني، فقط سألني عدة أسئلة بالقسوة
Then said, “We sentence you to qisas [retribution]
قال لي: حكمنا عليك بالقصاص
You did such and such”
أنت فعلت هكذا
He asked, “What do you think of my sentence?”
وسألني: ما رأيك في حكمي؟
At that moment, I mocked the judgment
وهنا كنت مستهزئ بالحكم
I didn’t take it seriously. I was just a cigarette trader,what does qisas have to do with that?
ومستهتر لأني أنا تاجر سجائر !ماهي علاقتي بحكم القصاص
Why should I be sentenced to retribution for cigarette trading?
ومن أجل ماذا؟ من أجل تجارة السجائر يحكم عليّ بالقصاص؟
They judged me as a corrupter on earth
حاكموني كحكم المفسد في الأرض
But “corruption on earth” means armed robbery and banditry
والإفساد في الأرض هو الحرابة وقاطع الطرق
Armed assault,not cigarette trading
السطو المسلح، وليس تاجر سجائر
And today, the whole world smokes cigarettes
وفي يومنا الحالي العالم بأجمعه يشرب السجائر
Everyone smokes cigarettes
بأجمعه يشرب السجائر
Even alcohol existed in the time of the Companions
والخمر موجود منذ زمن الصحابة
But now, in the time of these “new Companions,”
واليوم على زمن هؤلاء الصحابة الجدد
They want to cut off heads and hands
يريدون أن يقطعوا الرؤوس والأيدي
But there’s no power or strength left,today, they’re strong and we’re weak
لكن لاحول ولا قوة، اليوم قوتهم وضعفنا
He asked me, “What do you say about the judgment?”
فقال لي: ماذا تقول بالحكم؟
I said, “Me?”,I wasn’t afraid, I was relaxed
قلت له: أنا، كوني مستهتر بالحكم
I wasn’t scared at all, I was at ease
ولم أكن خائف وكنت بكل أريحيتي
I told him, “I’m satisfied with your judgment.” When I said that, they were surprised
قلت له: أنا راضِ بحكمك وعندما قلت له: راض بحكمك، تفاجؤوا
He said, “Why are you satisfied?” I said, “Isn’t this God’s decree, the Almighty?”
قال: لماذا أنت راض بالحكم؟ قلت له: أليس هذا حكم ربنا سبحانه وتعالى
“You’re ruling by God’s sharia, and I’m content with God’s law”
وأنت تحكم بشرع الله وأنا راضي بشرع الله
Then he said to me
:هنا، قال لي
“What will you say to the seven-member committee?”
ماذا تقول للجنة السباعية؟
I said, “Who are the seven-member committee?” He said, “They’re the sheikhs, because your file will be sent to them”
قلت له: من هم اللجنة السباعية؟ قال: هم المشايخ، لأن ملفك سيرفع إلى المشايخ
I said, “What difference will my words make?”
قلت له: كلامي ماذا سيقدم ويؤخر؟
“You already sentenced me to qisas,what can those sheikhs do now?”
أنت حكمت عليّ بالقصاص ماذا سيفعل المشايخ هؤلاء؟
He said, “Say whatever you want to tell them”
قال: مثلما تريد قل لهم
I said, “Send them my regards and tell them the Sheikh’s judgment is false upon falsehood”
قلت له: أبلغهم سلامي وقل لهم: أن حكم الشيخ باطل بباطل
Your entire verdict is invalid upon invalid
حكمك كله باطل بباطل
My case is about cigarettes, and you accused me of adultery and other charges
أنا قضيتي السجائر وأنت أدخلتني بقضية زنا وغيرها
Just to sentence me to execution
كي تحكم عليّ بالقصاص
How can you sentence me to execution while I’m blindfolded, shackled, and standing on my feet?
كيف تحكم عليّ بالقصاص وأنا معصوب العينين ومقيد وأنا أقف على قدمي؟
Then one of them stood up
فنهض أحدهم
And hit me
وضربني
He punched me in the stomach and I fell to the ground. They held me as another came from behind and hit me
لكمني على بطني، وسقطت أرضاً كانوا يمسكون بي وجاءني أحدهم من خلفي وضربني
Of course, I was blindfolded and didn’t know where the blows were coming from
طبعاً أنا معصوب العينين ولا أعرف من أين يأتيني الضرب
When he hit me, I said, I accept the judgment and law of God Almighty
:عندما ضربني، قلت لهم أقبل بحكم وشرع رب العالمين
When they shackled my left hand, I lifted the cloth blindfold from my eyes
وعندما ربطوا يدي اليسرى بالأغلال، رفعت العصبة القماشية عن عيني
I looked and saw that everyone was masked, and at the investigation door
نظرت وإذ الجميع كان مقنعاً ويوجد على الباب التحري
There was a black vehicle for transporting prisoners, marked “Judicial Police”
سيارة سوداء لنقل المساجين " كتب عليها "الشرطة القضائية
When they issued execution sentences
هم عندما يصدرون أحكام القصاص
They handed the sentenced prisoners to the Judicial Police, which handled executions and amputations
يسلمون المحكومين للشرطة القضائية وهي مختصة بالقصاص وبقطع الرؤوس واليدين
At that moment
حينها
Terror, death, and pain fell upon me
نزل عليّ الرعب والموت والألم بالفعل
It was a situation no one would envy, terrible to the point that
كان موقف لا أحسد عليه، سيء لدرجة
It truly defies description, no matter how I try to explain it
موقف لا يوصف حقيقةً مهما حاولت وصفه
When I saw the Judicial Police and their black vehicle parked there
عندما شاهدت الشرطة القضائية وسيارتهم السوداء واقفة
I saw my friend, Ibrahim al-Fakkash
"فوجدت صديقي "إبراهيم الفكاش
And another man, both shackled
وشخص آخر مقيدين
They hit me immediately
مباشرةّ ضربوني
Blindfolded me again, put a black bag over my head, shackled me, and made me sit down
وعصبوا عيني وضعوا كيس أسود في رأسي قيدوني بالأغلال وأجلسوني
I felt that Ibrahim al-Fakkash, out of fear, was repeating, “There is no god but God”
فشعرت إن "إبراهيم الفكاش" من الخوف يردد لا إله إلا الله
I crawled toward him
أتيت زحفاً واقتربت منه
And it was sunset time
وقد أصبح وقت الغروب
I asked him, Are you al-Breiwi?
سألته من أنت "البريوي"؟
He said, Yes. I asked, What did they do?
قال لي: أجل قلت له: ماذا فعلوا؟
He said, They sentenced me to execution
قال: حكموا عليّ بالقصاص
Then we cried,not because we wanted to, but out of sheer terror
حينها كنا نبكي ولا نبكي رغبةً منا، ولكن من شدة الخوف
Our fear wasn’t only of death or being shot
وخوفنا ليس من الموت فقط وأن يطلقوا رصاصة علينا ونموت
But from imagining them holding our heads and slitting our throats with a knife,that’s what truly terrified us
الخوف يكمن في تخيلنا لمشهد مسكه لرؤوسنا وحز رقابنا بالسكين، هنا يمكن خوفنا
Every second we were dying millions of times inside
في كل ثانية كنا نموت فيها ملايين المرات
Or a billion times,each time imagining the knife descending on our necks
أو مليار مرة، فعندما نتخيل لحظة نحرنا بالسكين، وإنزالنا من السيارة على نقطة ما
We had already seen ISIS videos showing people being slaughtered with knives
ونحن رأينا سابقاً إصدارات التنظيم وكيف يذبحون الناس بالسكاكين
Those scenes stuck in my mind, and I imagined the blade cutting through my neck
فبقيت تلك المشاهد عالقة في مخيلتي وكنت أتخيل لحظة نزول السكين على عنقي
We cried from fear
فكنا نبكي من شدة الخوف
We knew well who ISIS were,they had no mercy, no compassion
ونحن نعرف جيداً من هم تنظيم داعش حيث لا يوجد لديهم رحمة ولا شفقة
The third, the fourth, and others came, but one person remained
جاء الشخص الثالث والرابع وغيرهم ولكن بقيّ شخص واحد
It was during Ramadan, and we were fasting
وكنا في شهر رمضان وصائمين
As you know, at sunset, when the call to prayer begins for those fasting
وفي وقتها كما تعرفون الصائم عند آذان المغرب
Ibrahim al-Alkan said, I want water
وإذ "إبراهيم العلكان" يقول لهم: أريد ماء
Before you cut off our heads, we ask you to bring us water,we are fasting
قبل أن تقصوا رؤوسنا نطلب منكم أن تحضروا لنا الماء، نحن صائمون
So they brought us water
فأحضروا لنا الماء
We couldn’t see, because we were blindfolded
ونحن لا نعرف، لأننا كنا معصوبي الأعين
They gave the water to Ibrahim
أعطوا "إبراهيم" الماء
When he drank, the water got stuck in his throat from fear
"عندما شرب الماء "إبراهيم وقف الماء في حلقه من شدة الخوف
It lodged in his throat, and he began choking
علق الماء في حلقه فاختنق وبدأ بالغرغرة
I was so terrified, I thought they were strangling us one by one
ومن شدة خوفي ظننت أنهم يخنقونا واحداً تلو الآخر
At first, when we heard the sunset call to prayer, we relaxed, thinking no execution would happen then
نحن بدايةً عندما سمعنا آذان المغرب ارتحنا وقلنا في هذا الوقت لا يوجد قصاص
Because they usually wanted crowds to film their productions
لأنهم يريدون تجمع الناس ليصوروا إصداراً لهم
So when the call to prayer came, we felt some relief, knowing that executions never happened at sunset or night
فعندما أذن المغرب ارتحنا قليلاً لأن في وقت المغرب والليل لا يوجد قصاص
They never carried out executions at that time
ولا يقيمون حد القصاص على أحد
When Ibrahim started choking, fear overtook me
عندما اختنق "إبراهيم" تملكني الخوف
I crawled backward and ended up in the arms of my friend al-Breiwi
حينها رجعت إلى الخلف زحفاً "وإذ بي أصبحت بحضن صديقي "البريوي
When I stretched out my right hand, I touched the shoe of one of the ISIS members
وعندما مددت يدي اليمين أمسكت بحذاء أحد العناصر
Each of us had an ISIS member standing right beside him
وإذ كل شخص منا يقف بجانبه عنصر من عناصر داعش
I jumped into al-Breiwi’s arms and told him, They’re going to strangle us one by one
"فقفزت في حضن "البريوي وقلت له: سيخنقوننا واحداً تلو الآخر
Then they brought the last person,I think it was Baraa al-Ano,and shackled him
فعندما أحضروا الشخص الأخير وهو على ما أظن "براء العنو" وربطوه بالأغلال
They put us inside the vehicle
وضعونا داخل السيارة
We could see a little from under the blindfold. Inside the vehicle were sharp metal pieces and swords
كنا نرى قليلاً من أسفل العصبة القماشية ووضعوا في السيارة قطع معدنية حادة وسيوف
It felt like we were in a scene from the “Khalid ibn al-Walid” series from the sword era
"وكأننا في مسلسل "خالد بن الوليد على زمن السيوف وغيرها
They put us in a small isolated room with only a toilet
دخلنا إلى غرفة صغيرة منعزلة ويوجد فيها فقط دورة مياه
A small room with a toilet recently prepared and designated for us
غرفة صغيرة ويوجد بها دورة مياه أعدوها حديثاً ومخصصة لنا
There was a small window in the wall like this
يوجد نافذة صغيرة بالجدار بهذا الشكل
It had thick iron bars
يوجد فيها قضبان حديد غليظة
They brought us new iron chains,thick ones, not thin
أحضروا لنا سلاسل حديدية جديدة وكانت سلاسل غليظة وليست رفيعة
As if they were meant to restrain some giant beast
كأنهم يريدون ربط وحش ما عملاق
Like in American or foreign movies
ويوجد في الأفلام الأمريكية والأجنبية
There was a huge gorilla in one movie that they enlarged with cameras and computers
كان يوجد غوريلا ضخم في أحد الأفلام حيث أنهم كبروه بواسطة تصوير الكاميرات والحاسوب
It felt like they were chaining a giant gorilla with those massive chains
فكأنهم يربطون غوريلا ضخم بسلاسلهم الغليظة هذه
The chains were so thick that the prisoner couldn’t even move his hand
وبسبب غلاظة السلاسل الحديدية لا يستطيع السجين حتى تحريك يده
They shackled us with those chains, and between each person there were 26 links
وقيدونا بهذه السلاسل وكان بين الشخص والشخص الآخر 26 حلقة
The chains were white and new
والسلاسل لونها أبيض وجديدة
Abu Seif told me he had bought them especially for me, of the expensive kind
:حيث أن "أبوسيف" قال لي أنه اشتراه خصيصاً لي من النوع الثمين
He said he bought them exclusively from Qoutli Street
واشتراه من "شارع القوتلي" حصرياً
They also brought 7 locks
وأحضروا لنا 7 أقفال
They placed the chain on my hand and locked it with a padlock
مثلاً هذه السلسلة الحديدية وضعوه على يدي وقفلوه بالقفل
Then left 26 links’ space, chained my friend’s hand, and locked it too
ومن ثم تركوا مسافة 26 حلقة وقيدوا يد صديقي الثاني به وقفلوه بيده أيضاً
And so on
وهكذا
The first prisoner was Ibrahim al-Fakkash, known as al-Bariwi
أول سجين كان ابراهيم الفكاش”البريوي”
And I was second
والثاني أنا
Ibrahim al-Alkan fell ill
آخر سجين كان ابراهيم العلكان
Then they fasten the chain to the wall
وبعدها يربطون الجنزير في الجدار
Ibrahim al-Fakkash was at the front, and the other end of the chain was fastened to the wall
في المقدمة ابراهيم الفكاش وطرف الجنزير الآخر يربط في الجدار
The group cell was reserved for just the seven of us
كان المهجع مخصص لنا نحن السبعة فقط
They used to bring us a plate of oil and thyme
كانوا يجلبون لنا صحن زيت وزعتر
They would come in wearing masks and bring us food
ويدخلون إلينا وهم مقنعون ويقدمون لنا الطعام
I used to tell Al-Bariwi, our charge isn’t about the cigarette trade
"كنت أقول "للبريوي نحن تهمتنا ليست بسبب تجارة السجائر
They chained us and sentenced us to execution
فقد ربطونا بالسلاسل وحكموا علينا بالقصاص
And today this man comes in bringing us food while masked, and we’re bound with iron chains
واليوم يدخل علينا هذا، ويجلب لنا الطعام وهو مقنع، ونحن مقيدون بالسلاسل الحديدية
They even spoke to us through cameras and loudspeakers, telling us to move back
حتى أنهم يتكلمون معنا بواسطة الكاميرات ومكبرات الصوت ويقولون لنا: ارجعوا إلى الخلف
So we’d retreat and hide in a corner of the room while they brought in a plate of oil and thyme
حتى نلجأ ونختبئ بزاوية الغرفة لكي يجلبوا لنا صحن الزيت والزعتر
We’d eat like that, and during the first 7 days, we didn’t eat anything until an emir came in
كي نأكل ونحن في أول 7 أيام لم ناكل شيء, حتى دخل علينا أمير
He was from the Al-Dabba family, his name was Abu Saqr
"وهو من عائلة الضبة اسمه "أبو صقر
May God grant him wellness, guide him, and forgive him
أعطاه الله العافية، ووفقه الله، وسامحه الله
May God forgive him in this life and the next
سامحه الله في دار الدنيا ودار الأخرة
He came to us and started sitting with us every day for half an hour
جاء إلينا وبدأ يجلس معنا كل يوم مدة نصف ساعة
He would tell us prophetic hadiths
ويعطينا الرجل أحاديث نبوية
May God bless him and guide him
بارك الله به ووفقه الله
And protect him for his children, God willing
ويحفظه لأولاده إن شاء الله
He began forcing us to eat, like how one feeds a patient in intensive care
بدأ يجبرنا على الطعام مثل الشخص المريض في العناية
He’d put a bite of bread in our mouths, forcing us to eat
تضع لقمة الخبز في فمه بدأ بإجبارنا على أكل الطعام
He started easing our suffering a little
وبدأ يخفف علينا قليلاً
We stayed like this under Abu Saqr’s care
"تقريباً بقينا على هذا الحال عند "أبو صقر
For about three and a half months
ما يقارب ثلاثة أشهر ونصف
Around three and a half months, or about three months and 20 days
أو ثلاثة أشهر وعشرين يوماً تقريباً
When Abu Saqr’s shift ended, another would take over at night
"كانت تنتهي مناوبة "أبو صقر ويأتي شخص أخر للمناوبة ليلاً
No one dealt with us except Abu Saqr and the plate of thyme
لا أحد يتعامل معنا إلا "أبو صقر" وصحن الزعتر
I fell ill
وقد مرضت
And the weather turned cold
وأصبح الجو بارداً
It’s honestly painful to talk about
أعني شيء من المؤسف التكلم عنه
It wasn’t a human act
هذا ليس بفعل إنساني
Nor an Islamic one, not even something the Jews of Khaybar would do
وليس بفعل إسلامي وشيء لا يفعله يهود خيبر حتى
Because 7 of us sentenced to execution were chained with iron shackles
بسبب أننا 7 أشخاص حُكم علينا بالقصاص ومقيدين بالسلاسل الحديدية
And there were 27 links between each man
وبين الشخص والآخر 27 حلقة
When I needed to go to the toilets
وعندما أريد الذهاب إلى دورات المياه
God is witness to what I say
والله شاهد على ما أقول
And I wanted to sit to relieve myself
وأريد الجلوس في دورات الحمام لقضاء حاجتي
When I sat, my friend next to me had to bend toward me
عندما أجلس صديقي الثاني يجب عليه الانحاء إليّ
The third had to bend his body, and the fourth had to stand over me
والثالث يجب أن يحني جسده والرابع يجب أن يقف فوقي
Meaning four of us stood in the toilet so one could relieve himself, may God honor you
يعني 4 أشخاص يقفون في دورات المياه من أجل أن يقوم أحدنا أعزكم الله بقضاء حاجته
What kind of Islam is that? What sharia allows it?
في أي إسلام هذا وبأي شرع، عندما يقيد المسلم
Seven Muslim men chained together, entering the toilets three or four at a time
سبعة أشخاص مسلمين يقيدون بالسلاسل ويدخلون كل 3 و4 أشخاص سوية إلى دورات المياه
It was disgusting behavior
وسيرتها منقودة
And when one of us got sick
وعندما يمرض أحدنا
Many of the young men got diarrhea, or someone needed to urinate, it was obvious
وأصاب الإسهال الكثير من الشباب أو أحد يريد التبول واضح يعني
We all had to wake up, because between me and the next man were 26 links, so all 7 of us had to get up
فيجب أن نستيقظ نحن السبعة، لأن بيني وبين صديقي 26 حلقة، فيجب أن نستيقظ نحن السبعة
Especially when one of us was sick with diarrhea
خاصة عندما يكون أحدنا مريض وأصابه إسهال
We stayed like that for about three and a half months, or three months and 20 days
فبقينا على هذا الحال ما يقارب 3 أشهر ونصف أو 3 أشهر و20 يوماً
Our daily routine among ourselves
والنظام اليومي بيننا
We had no real routine, only reading the Quran, crying, and supplicating
لم يكن لدينا أي نظام يومي نظامنا الوحيد قراءة القرآن والبكاء والدعاء
Asking God to free us and the nation of Muhammad
عسى الله أن يفك أسرنا وأسر أمة محمد
At night, we’d sit
عندما نجلس طوال الليل
Reciting the Quran and praying Fajr until sunrise
نقرأ القرآن ونصلي صلاة الفجر حتى طلوع الشمس
We’d fall asleep drowsy, still in our chains
ونسقط نعساً بقيودنا
We barely slept half an hour or less before waking up in fear,some crying, some deep in thought
وبالكاد ننام نصف أو ربع ساعة وبعدها نستيقظ خائفين بعضنا يبكي وبعضنا يفكر
Some would sit alone in the corner, imagining death
ومنا من يجلس بمفرده في زاوية الغرفة ويتخيل الموت
When they were about to execute one or a group, the organization would film an ISIS video
حينها عندما كانوا يقصون أحد المحكومين أو مجموعة محكومين يصور التنظيم إصداراً لهم
On a disc or flash drive
بواسطة القرص أو ذاكرة التخزين
Abu Seif brought us a flash drive back then, and we watched it
"أحضر لنا "أبو سيف ذاكرة تخزين في تلك الأيام وكنا نشاهدها
It was like horror movies, we were sentenced to death, and he made us watch people being beheaded
بمثابة أفلام الرعب، ونحن محكومون بالقصاص وهو يجعلنا نشاهد كيف يقصون أعناق الناس
May God not grant him success in this world or the next
لا وفقه الله لا في الدنيا ولا في الأخرة
He showed us footage of an execution slaughterhouse in Deir ez-Zor Province
وضع لنا ذاكرة التخزين وعرض لنا مسلخاً للقصاص في محافظة دير الزور
Where they executed 35 people hanging from sharp iron hooks
حيث أنهم قصوا 35 شخصاً معلقين بواسطة علّاقات حديدية ذات سن حاد
One emir was carrying two men like this, wearing a short white robe,he was from Deir ez-Zor
وأحد الأمراء يحمل شخصين هكذا ويرتدي ثوب أبيض قصير وهو من مدينة دير الزور
He carried two men like that
يحمل شخصين هكذا
He killed them and hung them on iron hooks
قتلهم وعلقهم بواسطة علّاقات حديدية
Then Mustafa, known as Abu Seif
"وهنا "مصطفى" الملقب "أبو سيف
Said to me, “Look, Talal al-Shuweimi, do you see the execution prep, Talal al-Shuweimi?”
يقول لي: انظر يا "طلال شويمي" التعبئة
Sometimes the hallucinations and fear cause sicknesses like diarrhea, chills, and psychological illness
أحياناً الهلوسة والخوف تسبب أمراض مثل الإسهال والبردية والأمراض النفسية
There was a man with us named Qadri al-Dabba
"وكان يوجد معنا شخص اسمه "قدري الضبة
Qadri al-Dabba started screaming in his sleep
قدري الضبة" بدأ الرجل وهو نائم يحلم"
His eyes bulged, foam came out of his mouth,he became seriously ill, not normal at all
ويخرج عيونه ويخرج الزبد من فمه حيث أن "قدري الضبة" مرض بشكل غير طبيعي
Interviewer: Did the organization help him, or did they leave him to suffer?
المحاور: هل قدم التنظيم المساعدة لهذا الشخص أم تركوه يعاني؟
They didn’t give him anything, his fits would come every 4 or 5 hours
لم يقدموا له شيء لأنها بدأت تأتيه حالة استفزازية كل 4 أو 5 ساعات
One time, I fell sick myself
وفي إحدى المرات أنا مرضت
I got chills and severe diarrhea inside the prison
في السجن أصابني بردية وحالة إسهال شديد
It knocked me to the ground, and I was near death
أدت إلى إسقاطي على الأرض وكنت على وشك الموت
By God’s power, I recovered
وبقدرة الله سبحانه وتعالى تعافيت
My friends spoke to the ISIS members, but they didn’t give me injections or any help
وطبعاً تحدث أصدقائي مع عناصر التنظيم فلم يقدموا لي الحقن ولا شيء آخر
That happened during the days I was sentenced to death
حدث ذلك في الأيام التي حكمت بها بالقصاص
I don’t know if my illness came from fear or was a real sickness
لا أدري سبب مرضي هو الخوف أم هو مرض حقيقي
When I fell ill, there was a jailer under Abu Seif named Abu Abdul Malik
عندما مرضت، كان يوجد سجان عند "أبو سيف" اسمه " أبو عبد الملك"
He was from Tabqa, originally from Aleppo Province
من سكان مدينة الطبقة وأصله من محافظة حلب
He watched us through the cameras, even Ibrahim al-Fakkash started crying over me
كان يرانا من خلال الكاميرات حتى أن "إبراهيم الفكاش" بدأ بالبكاء عليّ
And Ibrahim al-Alkan recited Quran over me, rubbing my body and weeping, thinking I was dying
و"إبراهيم العلكان" بدأ بقراءة القرآن فوقي ويمسدون جسدي ويبكون عليّ، لأنني كدت أن أموت
And Ibrahim al-Ayyoub, nicknamed Shantar, was a simple, impatient man
"و"إبراهيم الأيوب" الملقب "شنتر كان رجل عديم الصبر وعلى نيته
He stood up, started smashing the door, shouting, “Talal al-Shuweimi is dead!”
فنهض وبدأ بتكسير الباب ويقول: "طلال الشويمي" مات
Abu Abdul Malik answered him
"فأجابه "أبو عبد الملك
And said, when he dies
وقال: عندما يموت
When he dies, let us know so we can take him out,that’s what Abu Abdul Malik said
عندما يموت أعطونا خبر "لكي نخرجه، وهذا كلام "أبو عبد الملك
Praise be to God, Talal al-Shuweimi is still alive by God’s grace
"والحمد لله رب العالمين "طلال شويمي إلى الآن على قيد الحياة بفضل الله
Abu Abdul Malik was later struck by an airstrike on his way to Tabqa
و"أبو عبد الملك" قصفته الطائرة وهو بطريقه إلى مدينة الطبقة
May God have mercy on him,I recited Al-Fatiha for him
وأعطانا عمره وقرأت عليه الفاتحة إن شاء الله
There were mediations everywhere
طبعاً الوساطات في كل مكان
But not before God Almighty,there’s no mediation, and no bribery works
إلا عند ربنا سبحانه وتعالى لا يوجد وساطة وبالطبع لا يوجد جيب للكف
When I was sentenced to death, neither my mother, my father, nor anyone could help me
ولا يوجد وساطة، وعندما حكم عليّ بالقصاص لم تنفعني أمي ولا أبي ولا أي شخص كان نفعني
Only God Almighty can help you
طبعاً رب العالمين هو الذي ينفعك
And your deeds help you in their eyes
وفي نفس الوقت أعمالك تنفعك بالنسبة لهم
But they still had mediations
لكن كان يوجد وساطات لديهم
One of my neighbors was detained
أحد الأشخاص من جيراني اعتقل
His name was Qusai Ahmad al-Omara,he paid them 5,000 dollars and was released
"اسمه "قصي أحمد العمارة دفع لهم 5 آلاف دولار وأخرجوه
In the final days, for example
في آخر الأيام مثلاً
I was under the death sentence when the judicial committee arrived
أنا في حكم القصاص بعدما جاءت اللجنة القضائية
They started bringing me my wife
أصبحوا يجلبون لي زوجتي
Then they started bringing me my second wife
وبدأوا يجلبون لي زوجتي الثانية
Of course, in exchange for money, whoever wanted the price of a motorcycle, I gave it to him
طبعاً بمقابل المال والذي يريد ثمن دراجة نارية أعطيه
And whoever wanted diesel for his house, I gave it to him
والذي يريد تعبئة مازوت لمنزله أعطيه
There were many things I benefited from after my family found out that I was in prison
وهناك أشياء كثيرة استفدت منها بعد معرفة عائلتي أني في السجن
We started playing openly
بدأنا باللعب على المكشوف
When my family found out that I was in prison
عندما عرف أهلي أني في السجن
My wives started
بدأت زوجاتي
And even
وحتى
Almost every day they came to visit me, one day they came, one day they didn’t
شبه يومياً يأتين لزيارتي أو يوم يأتون ويوماً لا
Of course secretly, so no one would see us outside
طبعاً بالخفية حتى لا يرانا أحد في الخارج
The prison was in a narrow corner facing my family’s house, and I saw them secretly
كان السجن في زاوية ضيقة مقابل منزل عائلتي وكنت أراهم سراً
They brought silver and gold coins, and their food was now paid for by us personally
ويأخذون ليرات فضة وليرات ذهب وطعامهم أصبح على حسابنا الشخصي
We were 7 people sentenced to execution
ونحن 7 أشخاص حكم علينا بالقصاص
Every day one of us paid for the food, the seven of us, and this prison
وكان كل يوم الطعام على حساب شخص منا، وطبعاً نحن السبعة وهذا السجن
It seemed that the jailers, the emir, and the rest of the group bringing food were all from poor families
على ما يبدو أنهم من العائلات الفقيرة السجان والأمير والجماعة كلهم والذين يجلبون الطعام
When they brought food, they gave it to the other prisoners
فعندما يجلبون الطعام يعطوه للمساجين الآخرين
Because the prison had two sections: one for the rest of the prisoners and one just for us seven
لأن السجن قسمين الأول لبقية المساجين ونحن السبعة مسجونين في قسم بمفردنا
We seven took turns. For example, if it was my turn, my wife knew that today was my turn
فنحن السبعة، مثلاَ دوري اليوم وزوجتي تعرف أن اليوم هو دوري
She brought food for me and for the guards, like fried chicken one day and grilled kebab another
تجلب الطعام لي وللشرطة الذين معي مثلاً يوم فروج مسحب ويوم كباب مشوي
She brought us ready meals from the market, and there was plenty. My turn came once a week since we were 7 people
وتجلب لنا طعاماً جاهزاً من السوق، والخير كثير ويلحقني في الأسبوع دور واحد، كوننا 7 أشخاص
Every day food was paid for by one of us, so my turn came once a week to bring the food
وكل يوم الطعام على حساب شخص منا فيلحقني في الأسبوع دور واحد بجلب الطعام
The food bill was about 75 to 100 thousand per month, all ready food from the market for us
وتقدر فاتورة الطعام ما يقارب 75 أو 100 ألف شهرياَ، وكله طعام جاهز من السوق لنا
And the ISIS members started sitting and spending evenings with us
ولجماعة التنظيم أصبحوا يجلسون ويسهرون معنا
They chatted with us, and we bought nuts and soft drinks, though we were shackled
ويتسامرون معنا ونشتري المكسرات والمشروبات الغازية وبالطبع نحن كنا مقيدين
They trusted us and learned our story
أمّنوا لنا وعرفوا قصتنا
They told us, “Your charge is collaboration with the Global Coalition, and you’re sentenced to execution”
قالوا لنا: تهمتكم على أساس العمالة للتحالف الدولي، وحكم عليكم بالقصاص
That actually helped us a lot in planning our escape
هذا الشيء ساعدنا في الهروب كثيراً
But once, we had a jailer who wasn’t just a jailer,he was also an emir in ISIS
ولكن في إحدى المرات كان يوجد لدينا سجان وليس سجان فقط بل كان أميراً في التنظيم
In the Mafarq al-Jazra area
في منطقة مفرق الجزرة
They said he was one of the “Kanas” family. I remember only his nickname, I forgot his name, but he was a good man too
يقولون له أنه من أولاد "الكناس" أتذكر فقط كنيته وقد نسيت اسمه، وكان رجل جيد أيضاً
In the morning, the emir Abu Saqr from the al-Dabba family came
في الصباح يأتينا الأمير "أبو صقر" من عائلة "الضبة"
He was on morning duty as the emir
في مناوبة الصباح هو الأمير
At night, the shift changed. That man left around sunset, and another took over
وفي الليل تتغير المناوبة، فيذهب هذا الرجل عند المغرب إلى منزله ويستلم شخص أخر مكانه
He was from Mafarq al-Jazra and was well known
وهو من منطقة مفرق الجزرة ومعروف
He told me he was married to two women
قال لي: أنه متزوج مرتين
Sometimes he came and sat with us, but ISIS put him under surveillance because he was kind and sympathetic to prisoners
وبعض الأحيان يأتي ويجلس معنا، فوضعه التنظيم تحت المراقبة، كونه رؤوف ومتعاطف مع المساجين
We paid him 7 million to bring us just a piece of a saw
دفعنا له في ذلك الحين 7 ملايين مقابل أن يجلب لنا قطعة منشار فقط
So we could escape, we told him
:حتى نهرب، وقلنا له
We’re 7 prisoners. If you can just bring us a small metal saw blade
نحن 7 مساجين، إن كنت تستطيع أن تجلب لنا فقط قطعة منشار من الحديد
Just so we could cut the big lock hanging on the wall
فقط لكي نقص القفل الكبير المعلق بالجدار
To escape
لكي نهرب
We told him each of us would give you one million. He said, “ISIS will kill me.” We said, “You’ll escape with us”
:وكل شخص منا يعطيك مليون، قال لنا سيقتلني التنظيم، فقلنا له: ستهرب معنا
Praise God, he was supposed to bring us the saw blade
وسبحان الله على أساس أنه سيجلب لنا قطعة المنشار
But the next day, they arrested him
ولكن في اليوم التالي اعتقلوه
They transferred him. We didn’t know whether he was detained or relocated, but we never saw him again after that
ونقلوه، ولا ندري إن كان اعتقل أو نقل ومن بعد ذلك اليوم، لم نر هذا الشخص مجدداً
When they tried to bargain with me
عندما ساوموني
They bargained with me a lot, even the well-known emirs
ساوموني كثيراً، ومن قبل الأمراء المعروفين
There were prominent figures among them
يوجد بينهم شخصيات معروفة
Specifically, one from the al-Amer family and one from the al-Mukhtar family bargained with me
"ومنهم بالتحديد شخص من عائلة "العامر وشخص من أولاد عائلة "المختار" تساوموا معي
They told me, “Bring us fertilizer”
تساوموا معي، وقالوا لي: اجلب لنا السماد
Fertilizer 33, the one they use to make explosives
سماد 33 وهو الذي يستخدمونه بصنع المتفجرات
They bargained with me to bring cigarettes and hide the fertilizer inside them for them
وتساوموا معي على أن أجلب السجائر، وأخبئ السماد بداخلها وأجلبها لهم
Many people bargained with me, not just them
وشخصيات كثيرة تساوموا معي وليس هم فقط
Even Abu Seif himself bargained with me to work with him
"شخصيات كثيرة جداً وحتى "أبو سيف بذاته تساوم معي على أن أعمل معه
And to pass on reports and information to him
وأن أنقل له الإخباريات والمعلومات
He told me, “Whatever you want in return, you’ll get it”
قال لي: الذي تريده مقابل لذلك ستحصل عليه
I told him, “I’m not that kind of man”
قلت له: أنا رجل لا أعمل هذا العمل
One day, the organization took me
في يوم من الأيام أخذني التنظيم
Abu Seif came to me. The first time, he came with Abu Khaled al-Idlibi and other men
جاءني "أبو سيف"، وفي المرة الأولى جاءني بها أبو خالد الأدلبي" وجاءوني جماعة آخرون غيره"
They took me away
وأخذوني
They said, “Come with us to carry out your sentence”
قالوا لي: هيا معنا من أجل تنفيذ الحكم بك
Of course
وبالطبع
They took me along with six other men
أخذوني مع 6 أشخاص أخرين
Among them was a man named Abdul Karim al-Ghaffaf
ومن ضمن الستة أشخاص "شخص اسمه "عبد الكريم الغفاف
He was from the al-Marandi clan
"وهو من عشيرة "المرندي
He was one of my uncles, and his charge was adopting Shia beliefs
وهو من أعمامي وكانت تهمته التشيع بالعقيدة الشيعية
An old man, about 80 years old
رجل مسن عمره تقريباً 80 عاماً
There was also another man from the al-Bu Assaf clan named Yasin al-Yasin
وكذلك يوجد شخص آخر "من عشيرة "البو عساف" اسمه "ياسين الياسين
Anyway
المهم في الأمر
There were six men, and I was the seventh
كانوا 6 أشخاص وأنا السابع
They took me in a car, and I felt that we had left the city
أخذوني في السيارة وشعرت أني خرجت خارج المدينة
They made us get out, and there was a cool breeze in the air
أنزلونا وكان الجو به نسمة هواء باردة
They made us kneel on our knees
أجلسونا على ركبنا
And when they made us kneel
وعندما أجلسونا على ركبنا
One of the emirs said, “Remove the cloth blindfold from Talal al-Shuweimi’s eyes”
قال أحد الأمراء: أزيلوا "العصبة القماشية عن عيني "طلال الشويمي
They removed the blindfold from my eyes
أزالوا العصبة عن عيني
Then I looked to my right and left and saw that everyone was lined up on both sides
عندها، نظرت إلى يميني ويساري ووجدت الجماعة كلهم مصفوفون على جانبي
They told them, “You did this and that, say the two testimonies”
:قالوا لهم أنتم فعلتم كذا وكذا، انطقوا الشهادتين
So they recited the testimonies, and each one was shot in the head
فنطقوا الشهادتين وضربوا كل شخص رصاصة في رأسه
I looked around and the place was full of trees,it used to be a Baath Pioneers camp
نظرت حولي كان المكان مليء بالأشجار حيث أنه معسكر طلائع البعث سابقاً
When we were kids, we used to go there in summer for school camps during the Assad regime
عندما كنا أطفال نذهب إليه صيفاً لعمل المعسكرات المدرسية في زمن النظام السوري
One of them said to me, “Talal al-Shuweimi”
"قال لي أحدهم: "طلال الشويمي
What do you want?
ماذا تريد أنت؟
I said, I don’t want anything. You brought me here and sentenced me to execution
قلت له: أنا لا أريد شيء أنتم جلبتموني إلى هنا، وحكمتم عليّ بالقصاص
He said to me
:قال لي
They removed the cloth blindfold from my eyes so I could see around me
وهم أزالوا العصبة القماشية عن عيوني لكي أرى ما حولي
Among them were well-known people,some of the senior figures in the ISIS state
كان بينهم أشخاص معروفون ومن كبار الشخصيات الموجودة في دولة داعش
High-ranking figures who are still alive today
من كبار الشخصيات ولا يزالون إلى الآن على قيد الحياة
He said to me
:قال لي
Now we’ll carry out the sentence and get rid of you
الآن سننفذ الحكم ونتخلص منك
Then another masked man came
وجاء شخص أخر مقنع
And said to me
:وقال لي
What is your last wish?
ماهي أمنيتك الأخيرة؟
At that moment
وهنا
I told him, to speak with my children
قلت له: أن أتكلم مع أولادي
He placed the pistol on my head
فوضع المسدس على رأسي
He said, “Say the two testimonies,” so I did
وقال لي: انطق الشهادتين، فتشهدت
Then he struck me
فضربني
As if he hit me in the head, but he fired the shot beside my ear
على أساس أنه ضربني برأسي ولكنه أطلق النار بجانب أذني
When he fired beside my ear, out of terror and horror
عندما أطلق النار بجانب أذني من شدة الخوف والرعب
My hands were tied behind my back, and I fell to the ground
كنت مقيد اليدين إلى الخلف، سقطت أرضاً
From the terror of it,it was like an American movie
من شدة الرعب، وكأنه فيلماً أمريكياً
I mean, something
أعني أنه شيء
Something indescribable, something even the Jews wouldn’t envy you for
شيء لا يوصف ولا يحسد عليه ولا يحسدك عليه حتى اليهود
Nor the Christians, nor Israel, nor even black devils would wish to see you in such a position
والنصارى وإسرائيل وحتى الشياطين ذات اللون الأسود لا تحسدك على مثل هذا الموقف
They wouldn’t even gloat over you
ولا تحب الشماتة بك
The last time I was imprisoned,as I said earlier,they transferred me from one prison to another
في آخر مرة دخلت بها السجن قلت لكم سابقاً أنهم نقلوني من سجن لسجن آخر
To a prison hidden in a corner
إلى سجن مخبأ في زاوية
Sadly, that prison was across from my mother’s house
وللأسف الشديد، كان السجن مقابل منزل أمي
My mother’s name is Zahia
"واسم أمي "زهية
And one of the emirs, named Muhammad al-Abadi
"وحتى أن أحد الأمراء واسمه "محمد العبادي
Used to tell me, “Zahia’s son, I saw Zahia walking in the garden”
"يقول لي: يا ابن "زهية لقد رأيت "زهية" تتمشى في حديقة المنزل
We were on the second floor, and he said, “I saw your mother”
حيث كنا في الطابق الثاني يقول لي: رأيت أمك
The man was joking with me
وكان الرجل يمازحني
We escaped from the prison during the days of the Euphrates Dam collapse in Raqqa
فهربنا من السجن، في أيام حادثة انهيار سد الفرات في مدينة الرقة
There were several of us, and that same man was with us
وكنا نحن ويوجد معنا هذا الشخص
His name was Abu Muhammad al-Abadi
"الذي يدعى "أبو محمد العبادي
May God bless and reward him
وفقه الله وجزاه الله خيراً
We made a hole in the prison wall
ثقبنا جدار السجن
He escaped with us, helped us, and watched the road. There were seven of us, and a car was waiting
وهو هرب معنا وساعدنا وراقب لنا الطريق هربنا نحن السبعة وكانت هناك سيارة تنتظرنا
We escaped by car, the seven of us
وهربنا بواسطة السيارة نحن السبعة
As for me, there’s a saying: they asked the nail, “Why did you go into the wall?”
:بالنسبة لي، هناك مثل يقول سألوا المسمار لماذا دخلت في الجدار؟
He answered, “From how much they hit my head”
فأجابهم: من شدة الضرب على رأسي
I didn’t sell cigarettes by choice, but I was an employee
أنا لم أتاجر بالسجائر رغبة بذلك لكنني كنت موظفاً
My salary was 12,000 Syrian Lira, working in the Water Authority
ومرتبي 12 ألف ليرة، موظفاً في مؤسسة المياه
After I started working, Air Force Intelligence raided my house and detained my brother, taking him to Sednaya Prison
بعدما توظفت داهمتني المخابرات الجوية واعتقلوا أخي وأخذوه إلى سجن صيدنايا
When they raided my place and I fled, I had 10 children
وعندما داهموني وهربت، كان لديّ 10 أطفال
They needed food and bread
يحتاجون الأكل والخبز
I bought a taxi without papers and drove it, but the income wasn’t enough
اشتريت سيارة تاكسي ليس لها أوراق وعملت عليها ولكن مردود التاكسي وحده غير كافٍ
And cigarette trade wasn’t punishable by execution or anything like that
وطبعاً تجارة السجائر لم يكن لها حكم قصاص ولا غيره
But the organization imposed execution on us, even though it wasn’t for cigarette trade
لكن التنظيم جلب لنا حكم القصاص ولم نحكم بالقصاص من أجل تجارة السجائر
Their judgments became vindictive
أصبح الحكم لديهم كيدي
They invented charges,collaboration, cigarettes, ammunition,just to sentence us to execution
تهمة العمالة والسجائر والذخيرة وهذه الأشياء ابتدعوها لكي يحاكموننا بالقصاص
I was forced into cigarette trade. I have children and pay rent for two houses
أجبرت أن أعمل بتجارة السجائر فأنا لديّ أطفال ولديّ منزلين في الإيجار
Every day I’d buy bread for 2,000 or 3,000 Syrian Lira, and there was no other work
وفي اليوم الواحد أجلب لهم خبزاً بقيمة 2000 و3000 آلاف، ولا يوجد عمل آخر
With the organization, either you join them or remain jobless
وبالنسبة للتنظيم إما الانتساب والعمل معهم أو تبقى بدون عمل
So how could I feed my children?
فكيف أعيل أطفالي؟
Should I trade cigarettes to earn a living and feed them, or let them starve to death?
أعمل بتجارة السجائر وأسترزق الله لإعالة أطفالي أم أتركهم يموتون جوعاً
Just like many others, there were about 2,000 people
مثلي مثل الكثيرون ، كان هنالك ألفي شخص يعملون في تجارة السجائر في “أراضي الخلافة”
And I was under a death sentence
لماذا فقط انا تم حكمي بالقصاص؟
Prison had a huge impact on me
كان للسجن تأثير كبير عليّ
When I first escaped from prison
في بداية هروبي من السجن
I started crying
بدأت بالبكاء
Tears of joy, not sadness
بكاء الفرح وليس بكاء الحزن
I began kissing the ground
وبدأت بتقبيل الأرض
I looked up to God Almighty, crying and shouting, breathing in the air
أنظر إلى الله سبحانه وتعالى وأبكي وأصرخ وأنظر وأشم الهواء
So many things happened to me
وهناك أشياء كثيرة حصلت معي
Prison affected me deeply,like forgetfulness, for example
أثر السجن عليّ كثيراً كالنسيان مثلاً
It left me with memory loss
حيث وقع أثر للنسيان في ذاكرتي
Tragic events that scarred me
كأشياء ومأساة حصلت معي
In my life, I never held hatred toward anyone
وأنا في حياتي لم أحمل الحقد على أحد
But they made my heart hard
لنهم جعلوا قلبي قاسياً
They killed the mercy inside me as a human being belonging to humanity
وقتلوا الرحمة التي في داخلي كإنسان منتمٍ للمجتمع الإنساني
They ignored so many rights,human rights, and my rights as a Muslim
وتجاهلوا الكثير من الحقوق كحقوق الإنسان وحقوقي كوني مسلم
As a father and provider for a family, for example
كوني أب لأطفال ومعيل لأسرة على سبيل المثال
They stripped the mercy from within me
نزعوا الرحمة من داخلي
There are still many things inside me
ويوجد أشياء كثيرة بداخلي
ISIS affected me deeply, and I still suffer from what’s called forgetfulness
أثر بها تنظيم داعش ومازلت أعاني من مشكلة تسمى النسيان
On top of that, the greatest hardship remains,that only God provides and sustains us
وفوق هذا الشيء تكمن المعاناة الأكبر ولا شك أن المعيش والمعيل هو رب العالمين
God Almighty is the Provider
والرزاق هو ربنا سبحانه وتعالى
For me, ISIS destroyed my life
بالنسبة لي تنظيم داعش دمروا حياتي
Why am I still struggling today to buy bread?
لماذا أنا اليوم أبحث على ثمن الخبز؟
Why am I looking for a job as a taxi driver for daily pay?
مثلاً وأن أبحث عن عمل كسائق سيارة أجرة عند أحدهم في الأجرة اليومية لماذا؟
What’s the reason?
ما هو السبب؟
Because of an ignorant man
!من أجل شخص جاهل
Because of an infidel
!من أجل شخص كافر
Who should be in prison for two or three years
لكي يدخل في السجن عامين أو ثلاثة أعوام
God willing, may the Almighty take from my life
وإن شاء الله رب العالمين يأخذ من عمري
And give it to his
ويضعه في عمره
Just so I live long enough until he gets out of prison, to see him even for one hour
فقط لأبقى على قيد الحياة لحين خروجه من السجن وأعطيه من عمري لأبقى ساعة واحدة
To settle my score with him
لكي أصفي بقية حسابي معه
An eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, and the aggressor is the unjust one
العين بالعين والسن بالسن والبادي أظلم
Everyone dies once
وطبعاً أي شخص يموت مرة واحدة
Better that than dying every hour before your children
أفضل من أن يموت في كل ساعة أمام أطفاله